翻译： @塔拉Tala
"Piano Concerto  in A Minor Op. 54-1"]
The only thing  I ever knew was cotton.
我以前只知道一件事，那就是棉花
It was hard work.
这是一项非常辛苦的工作
Now, you know cotton is ready  when the bud splits,
此时，当棉铃裂开时就意味着棉花已经成熟了
and the boll is star-shaped,
棉球是星形的
like a big 0l' star in the sky.
如同是镶嵌在夜空中一颗古老的星星.
Or like your big 0l' head.
或者就像是你的大脑袋.
Hold on, is that some cotton?
等等, 那是棉花吗?
Is that cotton?
那是个棉花吗?
But I didn't mind,
但我从不在意,
'cause I got to spend all day  working with my daddy.
因为我可以一整天都和爸爸在一起干活儿
- Hurry, take this picture.  - Take a picture of y'all.
- 快点, 拍张照片.  - 为你们所有人拍张照片.
Why don't everybody smile?
为什么大家都那么严肃?
Teeth.
露出牙齿.
Hattie, come on,  I need your help in the shed.
哈蒂, 过来  到小屋里帮我一下
Come on.
过来.
- Pa... where he taking Ma?  - Get back to work.
- 爸爸，他带妈妈去哪儿?  - 快回去干活
Cecil, come back here, boy.
塞西尔, 回来这里.
Mama!
妈妈!
Come here.
过来.
Look at me, boy.
看着我, 孩子.
Don't you lose your temper  with that man.
不要跟那个男人争论.
This his world.  We just living in it.
这是他的地盘儿  我们只是住在这里而已
You hear me?
听明白了吗?
Now, get on back to work.
那么，现在快回去干活儿吧.
Pa, what you gonna do?
爸爸，你准备怎么办?
H9)'-
喂.
' Dad!
爸爸!
- [gunshoq
Oh, my Lord.
噢，上帝呀.
Who you looking at?! Huh?
你看谁呢?! 啊?
Who wants to go next?!  You get back to work.
还有谁不想活了?!  回去干活儿.
Hey, you. Get some of the hands  to help dig a hole for his pa.
喂, 你. 去找几个人挖个坑把他爸爸给埋了
Hurry UP!
快点!
Stop crying-
不要哭了.
I'm gonna have you  in the house now.
现在我要带你去房子里.
I'm gonna teach you  how to be a house nigger.
我会教你成为一名会做屋内服务的黑鬼
- He's coming.  - Yes'm.
- 他来了.  - 好的，夫人.
And quiet when you're serving.
上菜的时候最好不要出声.
I don't even want  to hear you breathe.
最好连呼吸声都不要让我听到.
Yes, ma'am.
是对, 夫人.
The room should feel  empty when you're in it.
你待在房间里的时候要形同空气.
It was much nicer working  in the house than in the field.
在房间里干活儿要比在地里干活舒适得多.
Crazy nigger, from the left.
你这个愚蠢的黑鬼, 要记得从左边开始.
Give me more.
多给我一点儿.
Hmm.
嗯.
When I got older, I knew  I had to go before he killed me, too.
我的年纪一天天在长大，我开始意识到  我一定得在他杀了我之前离开.
Part of me was scared to leave.
但与此同时，我却又害怕离开那里.
It was the only world I ever knew.
因为我从未离开过那个地方.
Ma, I took Pa's watch.
妈妈, 我带着爸爸的手表.
Ma?
妈妈?
Ma, I'm leaving.
妈妈，我要走了.
My mama never  spoke much after that.
那次事件之后，我妈妈开始变得沉默寡言.
I knew she'd miss me,
我知道她会想念我,
but I also knew she wanted me  to leave that place.
但是我也知道她希望我离开那个地方.
And even though  Miss Annabeth never said it,
还有，尽管安娜贝丝小姐对我的离开  从未讲过只言片语
I knew she'd miss me, too.
但是我知道她也一样会想念我.
I don't think God meant  for people to not have a family.
我不觉得上帝是有意想要拆散一个家庭
Outside the cotton fields was even worse  than I thought it would be.
棉花田以外的世界远远比我想像得还要糟糕许多.
No one would give me a job  nor food nor a place to sleep.
没有人愿意给我提供工作的机会  更不用说食物和睡觉的地方
Any white man could kill  any of us at any time
任何一个白人都有可能随时随地杀掉我们
and not be punished for it.
而且不用担心遭受惩罚.
The law wasn't on our side.
那时的法律不仅不会保护我们.
The law was against us.
而且....对我们很不利
I was hungry all the time.
每天我都饥肠辘辘
You know what can happen  to you, son?
孩子，你知道这样做的后果会是什么，对吗?
Get up.
起来.
I said, get up.
我说了，起来.
I'm gonna have to lie  to the boss man about that window.
那个窗户的事，我必须得跟老板撒谎
The good Lord say  we ain't supposed to lie.
可是上帝说我们不应该撒谎.
Sorry, sir.
对不起，先生.
Where's your ma and your pa?
你爸爸和妈妈在哪儿?
My ma crazy in the head,  and my pa got killed.
我妈妈的精神有点不正常  我爸爸被杀了
I'll make you  some ham sandwiches
我给你做几个火腿三明治
and send you on your way.
然后送你出去
The boss will be here  in a minute.
老板马上就到了
Sunday's our busiest morning.
星期天的早晨是我们最忙的时间.
You looking for some help?  I know how to serve.
你需要帮手吗?  我知道该如何伺候顾客.
You done broke our window,  you done stole our food,
你打碎了我们的窗户，还偷了我们的食物,
and now you asking for a job?
然后你还想在这里工作?
Back in Macon,  I'm a house nigger, a good one.
在梅肯的时候,我是个做屋内服务的黑鬼  我做得很不错
Don't you ever use that word, son.
不要再用黑鬼那个词了，知道了吗，孩子
That's the white man's word.
那是白人的词
It's filled With hate.
那个词充满了敌意
Didn't your father  ever teach you any better?
难道你爸爸没有教过你吗?
- Slow down.  - Yes, sir.
- 慢一点.  - 是，先生.
You got to look through their eyes.
你要学会看眼色.
See what it is they want.
通过他们的颜色就能知道他们需要什么
- Got it?  - Strokes.
- 明白了吗?  - 嗯，动作要很轻
- Yeah, I got it.  - Here.
- 是的，我明白了.  - 给你.
See what it is they need.
看看他们需要什么.
Right this way.
这边请.
Anticipate.
预测.
I'm sorry. I'm sorry, ma'am.
对不起，对不起，女士.
Bring a smile to the eyes...
要尽可能地让你的服务对像...
...of your principal.
露出微笑
Perfect. Perfect.
完美，非常完美
Don't forget to save me them chitlins.
别忘了给我留一些猪肠.
- Why you like chitlins so much?  - 'Cause they're good eating.
- 为什么你那么喜欢猪肠?  - 因为猪肠很好吃.
The manager of Excelsior, in DC,  he came by yesterday.
华盛顿Excelsior酒店的经理昨天正好路过这里
He offered me a job as a butler.
他给我提供了一份男仆的工作
He must be paying you  top dollar, huh, boss?
他肯定会付你最高的薪水吧，老板?
Yeah.
嗯.
I was thinking about taking it,  but I don't know.
我正琢磨着要不要接受那份工作  我还不确定
I'm too old to be leaving  North Carolina.
我已经太老了，现在离开北卡罗来纳州  怕是不太合适
I'm just fine right here.
我在这里待着也很不错.
I told him to hire you.
我已经向他推荐了你.
I'm just now finding my way  around this hotel.
现在这家酒店，我也才刚刚摸出点门道
Ain't ready for all them  highfalutin white people,
还不足以去应付所有那些傲慢的白人,
all their fancy words.
还有他们的那些花哨的言辞
ours,
塞西尔, 我们都有两张面孔:  一张是我们自己的,
and the ones that we got  to show the white folks.
另一张则是我们给那些白人看的.
Now, to get up in the world,
现在，你想要在这个世界上立足
you have to make  them feel nonthreatened.
你一定不能让他们感觉到有威胁.
Use that, them fancy words  that I've taught you.
要学会使用我教过你的那些花哨的言语
White folks up north,  they like some uppity coloreds.
北方的那些白人们  他们喜欢傲慢的有色人种
Yeah.
是的.
I took that job  up in Washington, DC.
我接受了华盛顿的那份工作.
It was the most beautiful hotel  I'd ever seen.
那是我所见过的最漂亮的酒店
I hope it wasn't  too presumptuous of me
在你们经历了从布法罗到华盛顿
to have prepared a few spirits
如此漫长的旅程之后,我希望我为你们准备的
after your long journey here  from Buffalo.
这两杯酒不会太冒昧
The best decision that court ever  made was to slow this whole mess down.
法院有史以来作过的做好的决定  就是延缓了这场乱糟糟的乌龙事件
Nigger boys in school with white girls.  Who ever heard of such a thing?
让黑鬼小子和白人女孩们在同一所学校上学  有谁听说过比这更荒唐的事?
Next thing you know,  they'd be fornicating.
要真发生那样的事，那么接下来的事情  就会是黑人和白人开始通奸
Gentlemen, this here is different.  We could start another Civil War.
先生们, 现在的情形不同了  我们可以发动另一场内战.
Cecil, what do you think about niggers  going to school with white children?
塞西尔, 你对于黑鬼和白人小孩在同一所学校就读  的事有何看法?
To be honest with you,  Mr. Jenkins,
跟你说实话, 詹金斯先生
I tend to not be too concerned
我不是太关心美国的政治
with American or European politics.
或者欧洲的政治.
Nor should you, Cecil.  They're all criminals.
你的确也不应该关心, 塞西尔.  他们都是些罪犯
Earl Warren should be shot  and hanged.
厄尔·沃伦应该被枪决或者处以绞刑
That dumb son-of-a-bitch judge  is trying to integrate our schools.
那个婊子养的傻X法官居然想要整合我们的学校  （指取消美国学校的种族隔离制度）
I think Judge Warren is going to find  that quite challenging.
我想沃伦法官会发现执行这一裁决  将会面临巨大的挑战.
Damn right, Cecil. Damn right.
太对了, 塞西尔.你说得太对了.
Never in my life did I dream  I'd work in a place as fancy as this.
我以为从未梦想过我会在如此奢华的地方工作.
I never dreamed my life  could be so good.
我从未梦想过我会拥有如此棒的生活.
Gloria and I met working  at the Excelsior.
我和格罗瑞亚是在Excelsior酒店  一起工作时认识的.
She was a maid at the hotel,
那是她在酒店里做女仆,
but now her only job  was raising our two boys.
但是现在，她唯一的工作就是  养育和照顾我们的两个儿子
I made sure that they  never laid eyes on a cotton field.
我很确定他们从不知道棉花田是个什么东东.
- I got to pee.  - Not today. Don't try that.
- 我要去尿尿.  - 今天不行，别在琢磨花招了.
- Finish that homework.  - Where Louis at?
- 快点把作业写完.  - 路易斯在哪儿?
- He's taking the trash out.  - Working late again?
- 他去丢垃圾了.  - 又工作到这么晚?
- How was your shift?  - Beats working for a living.
- 值夜班感觉怎么样?  - 比上白班轻松多了.
I miss you at night, honey.
晚上我很想你，亲爱的.
Didn't you say you got to pee?  Go on, then.
你刚不是说你要去尿尿吗，那么快去吧
Wash your hands when you come  out of that bathroom, boy.
从洗手间出来的时候要记得洗手，小子.
- Good morning.  - Good morning.
- 早上好.  - 早上好.
Good morning, sir.
早上好，先生.
Mm-hm.
- Hey, Dad.  - Hey, Louis.
- 嗨，爸爸.  - 嗨，路易斯.
- You all right?  - Yeah, I'm fine.
- 你还好吗?  - 嗯，我很好.
- Good.  - That woman whose son got killed,
- 那很好.  - 儿子被别人杀了的那个女人
she's around doing speeches now.  What's her name, honey?
她正在四处发表演讲呢.  她叫什么名字来着?
- Mamie Till.  - Mamie...
- 玛米 提尔.  - 玛米...
Mamie Till. Mm.
玛米 提尔， 嗯
I remember that story just  like it was yesterday,
那事儿虽然都已经过去三年了
even though it was three years ago.
可感觉就好像是昨天才发生的一样
It was a dis-damn-grace  what they did to that boy.
那简直就TMD是一种耻辱  他们对那个男孩子所做的那一切.
Just for looking at a white woman.
就只是为了寻找一个白人女人而已.
Beat him up,
他们把他打个半死,
threw his body in the river,  killed him.
还把他丢到河里，淹死了他.
He wasn't no older than Louis.  He was 14 at the time.
他死的时候只有14岁，  还没路易斯大呢
- Crazy white folks down South.  - Thanks, Ma.
- 那些疯狂的白人南蛮子.  - 谢谢，妈妈.
At least we got it  a little better in DC, huh?
起码我们在华盛顿  处境要稍稍好一点，对吧?
Still treating us bad, too.
对待我们也一样很糟糕.
Get on down here, Charlie!  Wash your hands.
快过来这里, 查理!  把你的手洗了.
Louis said we should stop  taking the white man's shit.
路易斯说我们不应该再继续忍受那些白人的欺负了.
- Hey.  - Shut up.
- 喂.  - 闭嘴.
- Watch your mouth.  - Watch your mouth.
- 注意你的言辞.  - 注意你的言辞.
Hello, Gaines' residence.
你好, 这里是盖恩斯家.
Uh, yeah. Hold on, Mr. Kidgan.
嗯，对，稍等, 凯根先生.
- It's the boss man, Dad.  - What's he calling for?
- 是你老板，爸爸.  - 他打电话来有什么事?
When the white man call,  I always assume the worst.
每当白人打电话来的时候,  我总是会做最坏的打算.
Yes, sir?
你好，先生
I would have put money on it
我总是觉得那天
that I was getting laid off  or something that day.
我可能会被解雇，或者其他的类似的事情.
- Would you follow me, please?  - Yes, sir.
- 请跟我来  - 好的.
I'm Cecil Gaines.
我是塞西尔 盖恩斯
- It's a pleasure to meet you.  - You, as well.
- 很高兴见到你.  - 我也一样.
Have a seat.
请坐.
Are you political, Mr. Gaines?
你参与政治活动吗, 盖恩斯先生?
- No, sir.  - Good.
- 没有，先生.  - 那很好.
We have no tolerance  for politics at the White House.
在白宫，我们不会容忍任何与政治有关的事情.
- How'd you find me?  - I didn't.
- 你是怎么找到我的?  - 我没有找你.
You served R.D. Warner  at the Excelsior Hotel.
你在 Excelsior 酒店的时候曾为R.D.沃纳先生服务过.
He oversees operations  for the entire White House.
他负责整个白宫的运营事务.
- You made quite an impression.  - I don't recall.
- 你给他留下了很深刻的印象.  - 我不记得了.
Mr. Warner and myself make note  of potential staff around town.
沃纳和我一直在为白宫留意和挖掘  一些比较有潜力的员工.
Butler positions rarely open,
男仆这个职位很少会空缺,
as most stay on for 3O years or more.
因为大部分男仆都会在这个职位上  待30年甚至更久.
I know I was quite surprised  when I got the call.
我接到电话的时候非常惊讶.
It was a surprise  for me, as well.
我也觉得很惊讶.
As the White House maTtre d',  I normally hire the butlers.
作为白宫的总管,  男仆这个职位通常是由我来负责招聘的
Forgive me for saying this,  Mr. Fallows.
法洛斯先生，原谅我这么说...
I certainly wouldn't want to  be hired under circumstances
如果雇佣我会让你觉得不太舒服
that would make you  feel uncomfortable.
那么我也不想在这种情况下接受这份工作
Oh, really?
噢，真的吗?
You need butlers  that you've handpicked,
你需要一名你精心挑选的男仆
men to your liking  that will fulfill your vision
一个各方面都能让你
of a proper White House staff.
称心如意的员工.
Hmm.
嗯
Is that... Louis XIII?
那是... 路易十三?
These decanters are replicas
那些酒瓶是在雅尔纳克战场上
of metal flasks that were found  on the battlefield in Jarnac.
找到的那些金属酒壶的复制品
Correct?
对吗?
The Italians, they  know their wines,
意大利人很懂他们的葡萄酒
and the Irish, they certainly know  how to make a great whiskey.
至于爱尔兰人, 他们也非常明白  如何才能酿制出上好的威士忌
But I believe the French  have a distinct advantage
但是我相信法国人在酿制干邑白兰地方面
when it comes to Cognac.
有着独特的优势
(Test vrai?
我说得对吗?
Yeah, you'll make  a good house nigger.
嗯，你会成为一名很好的黑鬼仆人.
Would you care  for a demitasse?
要不要来杯咖啡?
Sometimes it just be  me and Faye up in here.
有时候我和法耶会待在这里.
Me, Faye  and a little scotch.
我，法耶，还有一点点威士忌.
Have a good time.
祝你玩得愉快.
That's how you do it.
你总是做的很棒.
You know how to throw  a bash, girl.
你知道如何成功地举办一场舞会
What did you do  to this potato salad?
这个土豆沙拉你是怎么弄的?
I'll tell you what I did.  I put some dill in it,
我来告诉你我是怎么做的吧  我在沙拉里放了一点小茴香
because I read in Woman's Day,  where pickles drown out the flavor
那是我在妇女日报上看到的  上面说酸黄瓜会盖掉其他味儿
and dill bring up the flavor.
而茴香则会提味儿.
- That's what you tasting right now.  - OK. Yeah.
- 你现在吃的就是那个加了茴香的东东  - 好吧.
- I like it.  - Make a difference, don't it?
- 我很喜欢.  - 跟以前有点点区别，对吧?
It really does.
还真是那么回事.
Girl, you must be so proud of Cecil.
塞西尔肯定让你感到特别骄傲吧.
You know he got that job hisself.  The White House called him,
你知道，他是靠自己的本事赢得了那份工作  是白宫打电话来找的他
- he didn't call the White House.  - He's a good man.
- 而不是他打过电话给白宫.  - 他是个很好的男人
- You got a good man.  - She's fun, man!
- 你嫁了个好男人.  - 她很开心呀!
Not like this one right here.  OI' sourpuss.
而不像是坐在这里的这位坏脾气的唠叨婆
- You still mad at me?  - I got reason.
- 你还在生我的气吗?  - 我生气是有原因的.
No, you don't. I told you,  I went down to the numbers spot,
不，你没理由生气啦，我已经跟你讲了  我去了那个玩纸牌的地方
played my little numbers,  got me some barbecue,
玩了会儿牌, 吃了点烧烤,
and then I went down...  I didn't even get nothing to drink!
然后，我又去了...  我真的什么都没喝!
I am so... I'm so sick of these  numbers spot stories, Howard.
我很烦... 我很烦再听你说什么打牌的故事，霍华德
How you expect me to believe you  was down at the numbers spot?
你怎能指望我还会相信你
Whether you believe it  or not don't mean it ain't true.
你信，或者不信  事实就摆在那里
- Come on, stop this mess.  - You want to do this right now?
- 好啦，别再吵了  - 你真的想现在吵架么
Come on, y'all.  Come on, come on, come on.
行啦，你们俩个, 行啦，行啦
You don't believe it, you don't  have to believe it, but...
你爱信不信，你也用不着相信  但是...
- Come on, y'all.  - Such a shuckster.
- 行啦，你们两个.  - 大骗子.
- You really want to do this right now?  - Stop this right now.
- 你真的想挑这个时候吵架么?  - 都马上给我闭嘴.
You need to pick on  somebody your own size.
你总得找个个头和你差不多的人比划吧
We are here to celebrate,  so y'all could be nice just one time.
我们在这里是为了庆祝塞西尔的新工作的,  所以你们两个能不能好好的哪怕就这一次也行.
You heard the lady.  Come on, get over here, let's celebrate!
你听到她说的话了吧  来吧，过来让我们庆祝庆祝
Celebrate.
庆祝
That's why I was out,  trying to make you happy.
那就是为什么我要出去的原因  我是为了让你开心嘛
- Y'all need to get a room.  - What? What?
- 你们俩需要找个房间吧.  - 什么，什么啦?
Ain't that the truth?  Or something.
难道不是吗
He drives me crazy. He just... Ugh!
他都快把我逼疯了.  他... !
You ain't, uh...  You want to come to the room with us?
你, 嗯... 你想跟我们一起进去吗?
No.
不.
- Hey, where the boys at?  - They upstairs in the back room.
- 喂，其他孩子在哪儿?  - 他们在楼上后面的房间.
Boys! Get on down here!  I need to see your face now!
小伙子们，下来这里吧!  让我看看你们!
- What y'all doing up there?  - Yes, congratulations.
- 你们在上面干嘛呢?  - 祝贺你.
Honey, when you gonna take me  to the White House?
亲爱的,你打算什么时候带我去白宫瞧瞧?
You want to go  to the White House, baby?
你想去白宫, 宝贝?
You know I want to go  to the White House.
你知道我想去白宫.
When you want to go?
那你想什么时候去?
- Don't play with me now...  - When you want to go?
- 别跟我瞎逗了...  - 你想什么时候去?
The White House,  now that's a big step up.
白宫,那可是一个很大的进步.
- Ooh!  - Yeah, it's exciting.
- 哇!  - 对，让我很兴奋.
Girl, you up in that house now!  I want to hear all the stories.
姑娘们，大家都去楼上吧!  我想听听所有的故事.
I don't know how many stories  you gonna hear,
我可不晓得你究竟想听多少故事,
'cause they done swore him  to some kind of secret code,
因为他们已经让他宣过誓
- and he can't tell me nothing.  - No. Girl, you give it to him right.
- 他什么都不能跟我透漏.  - 不会的，姑娘，只要你把他服侍好.
- Mm-hm! He'll tell you everything.  - That's the key right there.
- 他会告诉你一切的.  - 这就是关键.
You listening?
你听到了吗?
- Did you hear her?  - Who you been giving it to?
- 你听到她说什么了吗?  - 那你都服侍谁来着?
Well, if you was at home,  I could be giving it to you.
这个嘛，如果你一直待在家里  我服侍的那个人必然就是你.
I don't know  what you talking about.
我不知道你们在说什么.
Boys, y'all better bring  y'all little narrow butts down here!
小伙子们，你们最好把你们的瘦屁股挪到楼下来!
- Here they come.  - Called y'all 19 times.
- 他们来了.  - 都叫你们800遍了.
Boys, stop running through this house.  You know better than that.
小伙子们，别在房间里四处乱窜.  你们懂的.
Elroy! Get over here.  Come here.
埃尔罗伊! 过来这里
Give me some money.
给我点儿钱.
Nah. Tell them... Tell them what  you gonna be when you grow up.
告诉他们... 告诉他们等你长大了你准备干什么.
I want to work at the White  House just like Mr. Gaines.
我想要跟盖恩斯先生一样在白宫工作.
- Ah, that's my boy.  - Right there.
- 噢，那才是我儿子.  - 对.
All right, man.
好吧.
Louis! What you gonna be  when you grow up?
路易斯! 等你长大了你想干什么?
You gonna work at  the White House like your daddy?
你也想像你爸爸一样在白宫工作吗?
- I don't know.  - I'll tell you one thing.
- 我不知道.  - 我跟你说一件事吧.
I knew exactly what I wanted  to be when I was 13.
我13岁的时候我就已经非常确切地知道了我的理想.
Yeah, a number runner.
对, 要做一个赌棍.
I'm Cecil Gaines.  I'm the new butler.
我是塞西尔 盖恩斯  我是新来的男仆
Yes, sir.
是的，先生.
There are 16 full-time maids.
那里有16位全职的女仆.
We have six butlers,  four carpenters, two painters,
我们有六位男仆  四位是木匠，两位是油漆匠
seven electricians,  three dishwashers, three doormen,
七位电工,三位洗碗工, 三位门卫,
a full kitchen staff, including pastry  chef and three full-time calligraphers.
一位全职的厨房职工，兼任糕点师傅  还有三位全职的誊写员.
Two painters, seven  electricians, nine engineers...
两位油漆匠, 七位电工, 九位机修工...
Here comes Warner.
沃纳来了.
Uh, Mr. Warner, wanted to thank you  for the opportunity
沃纳先生, 我想谢谢你给我这个..
to work in the White House...
在白宫工作的机会...
Come on. Here we go.
算了，我们走吧.
Ma'am, I'm Cecil Gaines.  I'll be working with you here.
夫人，我是塞西尔 盖恩斯  我会在这里与您一起工作.
Mr. Gaines,  please don't do that.
盖恩斯先生,请不要那么做.
- Come on.  - Yes, sir.
- 走吧.  - 是的，先生.
Now, when lifting a plate,  never scrape the bottom.
端盘子的时候一定要小心不要刮花盘子点底部
Never listen  or react to conversation.
永远不要留意他们的谈话或者作出任何反应
- The room should feel as...  - Empty when I'm in it.
- 你待在房间里的时候...  - 要做到形同空气.
So then she says...
所以他们说...
Then she says, "Stick..."
所以他们说, "伸出来... "
"CK-"
"好 "
Then she starts  screaming and yells,
然后她开始尖叫,
"Stick your whole hand in!"  So I put my whole hand in.
"把你的整个手伸进去!"  所以我就把整个手伸进去.
Then she yells out,  "Put both hands in!"
然后她又开始大叫,  "要用两只手!"
"OK!"
"好的!"
Then she screams,  "Now clap!"
然后她又叫, "现在，拍手!"
I say, "I can't."
我说, "我不能. "
She looks up, smiles and says,
她仰起头，笑着说,
"See, I told you my..."
"你瞧, 我跟你说了我的... "
That ain't funny.
那一点儿都不好笑.
Hey, there he is!  Heard you were coming.
噢，他在这里!  我听说你要来
- What's your name?  - Cecil.
- 你叫什么名字?  - 塞西尔
- Cecil Gaines.  - That ain't funny.
- 塞西尔 盖恩斯  - 那不好笑.
I'm Carter Wilson, head butler.  Don't worry about Big Mo behind you.
我是卡特 威尔逊，这里的首席男仆.  别担心你身后的那个大块头.
That brother will steal your wallet  before you even knew it.
那哥们会趁你不注意到时候偷走你的钱包.
This brother in the mirror over here,  his name's James Holloway.
你从镜子里可以看到的那哥们  他叫詹姆斯 霍洛威
- He's my second in command.  - James.
- 他是我的第二把手.  - 詹姆斯.
Jackie Robinson or Willie Mays?
你是杰克 罗宾森还是威利 梅斯?
Why don't you shake  the man's hand first
为什么你不能在开始问你那些刁钻问题之前
before you start asking difficult  questions like that?
先跟这哥们握个手?
I just want to know  where the man's coming from.
我只是想知道他是打哪儿来的.
Look like the jury's still  out on that one, right?
看上去还没有得出结论，对吗?
Welcome.  Fancy Freddie give you the tour yet?
欢迎你. 范希 弗雷迪已经带你参观过了吧?
He did.  ls the Dodgers still... still losing?
是的. 道奇还是...  在输?
I might be able to answer that question  if Carter over here
如果卡特能在这里让他闭上他的大嘴巴
stop running his nasty mouth.
或者我能回答你的那个问题
Cut the shit  and let's get to work.
别扯淡了，我们去干活儿吧.
"Ain't That a Kick in the Head"]
- Ready.  - Lord, help us.
- 准备.  - 上帝保佑我们吧.
Don't be nervous, man.  Just go on and get to it.
不要紧张. 放轻松点，去吧.
You hear nothing,  you see nothing.
要做到充耳不闻, 视而不见
You only serve.
只要专心做好你的事.
Send federal troops to Little Rock?
要派联邦军队去小岩城?
If it comes to it, yes.
如果真要是到了那一步，那么是的.
I can't see any situation where  I'd send federal troops to the South.
我看不到有任何能让我派联邦军队去南部的理由
Ever. Could cause another Civil War.
从没有.而且那会引发另一场内战.
Sir, if the federal government  doesn't enforce Brown, then who will?
先生, 如果联邦政府都无法实施布朗案的裁决  那么还有谁可以呢?
The South must comply with the law.
南部一定要遵守联邦法律.
It's just gonna take some time  to adjust, that's all.
他们只是需要一点时间去适应而已
I understand, Mr. President,
我明白, 总统先生
but if Faubus continues to block the  Negro children, then what do we do?
但是如果福伯斯继续隔离黑鬼小孩  那我们要怎么办?
We must enforce  the Constitution.
我们必须要执行宪法的规定.
Give Faubus more time.
再多给福伯斯一点时间吧.
With a little persuading,  he'll back down.
还有，再劝劝他  相信他会作出让步的
We just want to move slowly.
我们只是不想太急功近利.
- How'd it go?  - I almost shit myself.
- 怎么样?  - 我都快尿裤子了.
I dated a girl once. Every time  I hit her, she shit herself.
我以前约会过一个女孩  每次我揍她的时候她都会尿自己一身
- What?  - Got no sense.
- 什么?  - 不要脸
- Shut up.  - You shut up.
- 闭嘴.  - 你闭嘴吧.
I put a towel down.
我放了一个毛巾在下面呢
You know, Marcella said  the very same thing last night
你知道，我昨晚送马塞拉睡觉前
just before I put her to sleep.
她也说到了相同的事情
- Wow. You put her...  - Just like I did Ed.
- 哇噢，你送她...  - 就像我对待埃迪一样.
I'd do it real quick.
我做得非常快.
' See you!  - Why?
- 你瞧你!  - 为什么?
Dang...  Got the popcorn all over the sofa.
讨厌... 沙发上到处都是爆米花
Your dad's gonna kill...
你爸爸会杀了...
Hey,Dad.
嗨，爸爸.
- Hi, Mr. Gaines.  - Hey, Dad.
- 嗨，盖恩斯先生.  - 嗨，爸爸
Hey, Elroy.
嗨，埃尔罗伊.
Louis, I told you about letting these  kids watch that show.
路易斯, 我跟你说过  要让那两个孩子们看其他的电视节目
It's too scary.  They're too young for it.
这个电影太恐怖了.  他们的年纪不适合看这个
Turn it off.
关掉吧.
All you got to do is smile pretty,
你需要做的就是要笑得甜美一点
and a man will forget  everything he ever learned.
让会让男人就会忘记一切
Where your mama at?
你妈妈在哪儿?
Miss Gloria tried staying up,  but she went to sleep.
格罗瑞亚小姐想要熬夜来着，但是她睡着了.
Elroy, ain't nobody  asked you nothing.
埃尔罗伊, 没人问你话.
Take your butt home before  your mama come up in here
在你妈妈来这里收拾我们大家之前
and whup the both of us.
你快点轱辘回家吧
- Come on, Dad.  - Go on.
- 得了，爸爸.  - 快走吧.
- Bye.  - Turn it off.
- 拜.  - 把电视关掉.
Don't go stomping up the stairs,  wake your mama up.
上楼梯的时候轻一点  别吵醒你妈妈
What is that?
那是什么?
Is that that Mamie Till stuff?
那是玛米 提尔的照片?
- I want to go to this.  - Absolutely not.
- 我想要参与这事儿.  - 绝对不行.
How come?
为什么?
Ain't no good can come of that.
那事儿不会带给你任何好处的
Dad, you heard what Mama said?
爸爸，你听到妈妈是怎么说的?
That mess right there  happened down South.
那些破事儿是发生在南部
- This could have been me.  - It happened down South.
- 但那个人也有可能就是我.  - 那是南部的事.
I got out of there so we  could have us a better life.
正因为我离开了那里  所以我们才能今天更好的生活
Right now, I'm working for the white  man, make things better for us.
眼下我在为白人工作  我只是为了让事情对我们更有利.
And not just any white man, either.
而且也不是所有的白人都那样
Put the lights off. Go to bed.
把灯关掉. 上床睡觉.
I have your chicken soup,  Mr. President.
我给你炖了点鸡汤,总统先生
Just set it on the table, Cecil.
先放在桌子上吧, 塞西尔
Yes, sir.
好的，先生.
Did you ever complete school, Cecil?
你有没有把学上完, 塞西尔?
I didn't go to school,  Mr. President.
我没有上过学,总统先生.
I grew up on a cotton farm.
我是在棉花农场里长大的.
I grew up on a farm.
我也是在农场里长大的.
Do you have any children?
你有孩子吗?
Yes, sir, I have two sons.
是的，先生，我有两个儿子.
Do they go  to an all-colored school?
他们是在综合学校上学的吗?  （非种族隔离学校）
Yes, sir, they do.
是的，先生.
What is it?
怎么了?
State Guard just blocked  all the colored kids again.
地方警卫队又把有色人种的孩子们挡在外边.
Faubus promised me the guards  would escort the kids in.
福伯斯跟我保证过那些警卫会护送孩子们进去
Governor of Arkansas lied,  Mr. President.
可见阿肯色州的州长在撒谎  总统先生.
What is wrong with him?  Why is he forcing me to do this?
他究竟有什么毛病?  为什么他非得逼我这么做?
Yes, sir.
是的，先生.
Our next move  needs to be bold and swift.
我们的下一步行动必须要大胆而且迅速
I have today  issued an executive order
今天我将签发一项总统命令
directing the use of troops  under federal authority
我们要发挥联邦军队的效用
to aid in the execution  of federal law
以确保联邦法令能在...
at Little Rock, Arkansas.
阿肯色州小岩城顺利施行.
This became necessary...
这是必须的..
When the president  sent those troops down to Little Rock,
总统派遣了军队前往小岩石城
it was the first time I ever seen a  white man stick his neck out for us.
那也是我第一次见到一位白人  为了我们黑人的权益而承担风险
I told Louis that the president was  gonna make things better for us.
我告诉路易斯  总统正在为我们争取更好的生活.
All graduations are long.  She was so nosy.
毕业典礼总是那么漫长  她还哔哔个没完没了.
I'm gonna make  some potato salad.
我去做点儿土豆沙拉.
Now he could see that I knew  what I was talking about.
现在他可以看到我所指的究竟是什么
That was wonderful.  I'm so proud of you.
那太美妙了  我真为你感到骄傲.
- Thanks, Mama.  - That hat looks stupid.
- 谢谢，妈妈.  - 那个帽子看起来好傻.
Your face looks stupid.
你的脸才看起来好傻呢.
- Proud of you, too.  - Dad, did you see...
- 我也为你感到骄傲.  - 爸爸，你有没有看到...
Don't start something in there.
别再在这里瞎嚷嚷了
Did you see one white kid  in my school?
你有没有在我的学校里看到任何白人孩子?
Why couldn't Louis see that  the president made things better for us?
为什么路易斯就看不到总统为了我们所做的努力W?
- Thank you.  - Cookie?
- 谢谢.  - 要点饼干吗?
- Cookies.  - Thanks.
- 要点饼干吗  - 谢谢.
Thank you.
谢谢
Boy, I told you  we was gonna be late!
我跟你说了我们会迟到的!
You cannot miss this bus!
你可不能错过这趟巴士!
- Oh, Lord have mercy.  - Wait, a sec. Wait, wait, wait.
- 噢，仁慈的上帝呀  - 等一下，稍等.....
- What?  - Got to say good-bye.
- 什么了?  - 我们必须得先说再见.
Bus can wait.
巴士是可以等的.
Tennessee is  a long ways away, Pop.
田纳西州离这里很远.
Fisk is a really  good school, Dad.
费斯克可是一所很棒的大学.
You can change your mind  and go to Howard.
你可以去霍华德大学.
I cannot believe you are still  talking about Howard University.
我简直不敢相信，都这会儿了  你居然还在扯什么霍华德大学
- He's going to Fisk.  - I know, I know. It's just...
- 他要去费斯克大学.  - 我知道，我知道，只是...
It's just so far away, that's all.
只是觉得离家太远了而已.
- That's the point.  - What's the point?
- 那就是重点所在.  - 什么重点?
Give me a cigarette, and don't  tell me you don't smoke.
给我支烟吧，而且可别跟我说你不抽烟.
- I don't have one.  - Come here.
- 我没烟.  - 过来.
- You know you want to cry, punk.  - Not for you.
- 你很想哭，是吧，傻瓜.  - 我又不是为你哭.
Look under your mattress.  I left you something.
回家后看一下你的床垫下面有什么.  我给你留了点东西
- I can't protect him down South.  - The South has changed, Cecil.
- 他在南方我就无法保护他了.  - 南方已经跟过去不一样了，塞西尔.
I'm too young for Playboy.
我还不到看“花花公子”的年纪呢.
The South ain't what it  was when you was there.
那里已经不再是你曾经待过的那个南部了.
Ma, Louis is leaving me  his filthy magazines.
妈妈，路易斯把他的色情杂志留给了我
- Stop lying on your brother.  - Why you slapping him?
- 别跟你兄弟瞎说.  - 为什么你要扇他呀?
He's the one with the magazines.
他才是拿着杂志的那个人.
- I love you, Mama.  - I love you, son.
- 我爱你，妈妈  - 我也爱你，儿子.
- I love you, Louis.  - I love you.
- 我爱你，路易斯  - 我也爱你
- I made you ham sandwiches.  - Thanks, Mama.
- 我给你做了火腿三明治  - 谢谢妈妈
Come on, Dad.
好了，爸爸
OK.
好吧
You're the first.
你是第一个
I know.
我知道
I'm really proud of you.
我真的很为你骄傲
I got to go, Dad.
我得走了，爸爸
I got to go.
我必须得走了
If you need anything, you call me.
如果你有什么需要，就打电话给我
- All right.  - All right?
- 好的.  - 好吗?
Bye, Mama.
拜 妈妈.
Bye, Louis.
拜 路易斯
It's all right.
没事的
Remind me again why  we're doing this, please.
请再提醒我一下为什么我们要这么做
Somebody? Tell me?  That look like a mugging to me,
有人能告诉我吗  那玩意看上去就像是一个苦瓜脸
- that's what that looks like.  - This is the art of French baking.
- 看起来就是那样  - 那是法国的烘培艺术.
Negro, please.  "Art of French baking."
得了吧，黑鬼.  别跟我扯什么"法国的烘培艺术 "
This is absolutely nothing.  That's what this is.
这很明显狗屁都不是.
- I don't...  - Boy's always so simple.
- 我不...  - 男孩子的头脑总是那么简单.
You want me to play with it?  I'll play with it.
你想让我玩给你看吗?  我来玩给你看吧
Play With it like this.
就像这样.
It'd be good if it had a little...  a little nipple on it.
这会很好看，如果再给它弄个小...  弄个小乳头在上面.
Come on, man.
得了，哥们.
That's how you play. You jiggle it.  You shake it, you know.
你不就是这么玩的吗.  你摇晃它. 你摆弄它.....
This fool.
这个傻子.
Good evening,  Mr. Vice President.
晚上好, 副总统先生
That looks like a tasty treat.
那看上去很美味呀
Yes, sir.
是的，先生
I brought you all something.
我给你们大家带了点东西来.
Thank you, Mr. Vice President.
谢谢你，副总统先生.
I don't want to say anything negative
我不想说任何不利于那个...
about that Kennedy boy.  I'm sure he's a real nice fellow.
肯尼迪男孩的事儿.  我很肯定他是个很友善的家伙
But do you really want that  spoiled rich son-of-a-bitch fuck
但是，你们真的想让那个被宠坏的...
to be your next president?
富人家的婊子养的家伙...  成为你们的下一任总统吗?
Think about it.
好好想想吧.
We'll cheer for you,  Mr. Vice President.
我们会为你加油的，副总统先生
Thank you, Cecil.
谢谢你，塞西尔.
Let me ask you something,  in all candor,
让我来问你点儿事儿吧  坦率的说,
as members of the Negro community,  what are your biggest concerns?
作为黑人社区的成员  你最关心的事情是什么?
Now, come on now, boys.
说说看，小伙子们
Don't be shy.
别不好意思.
Holloway, come on.
霍洛维，你说说
- Well, since you asked, sir...  - I did.
- 好吧，因为你问到了，先生...  - 对，我在问你
The colored help gets paid almost  4O percent less than the white help.
同样的活儿，支付给有色员工的薪水  比支付给白人的薪水要低40%
- Is that right?  - Yes, sir.
- 是这样吗?  - 是的，先生.
And it's very difficult for  the colored staff to be promoted.
而且有色员工基本没有升迁的机会.
I'll tell you what. When I'm president,  I'm gonna look into getting you boys
我告诉你吧，如果我是总统  我会为你们加薪
the raises and  the promotions you deserve.
并且让你们都得到升职.
That... that would be swell, sir.
那.. 那会很棒，先生.
- You got my word on that.  - Thank you, sir.
- 我向你保证.  - 谢谢你，先生
Now, you tell your people  to vote for me,
那么现在，你要让你们的人为我投票
and that's exactly  what's gonna happen.
然后我说的那一切将会实现
Give that to somebody.
把那个分给大家.
What do you mean, you don't  want to date nobody?
你说的是什么意思，你不想跟任何人约会?
After all these guys  that come after you?
尤其是有那么多人在追你.....
- Girl, please. I'm just...  - Like that one?
- 我只是...  - 比如那一位?
I'm talking about you and Isaac.
我们现在说的是你和艾萨克.
Now, come on,  tell me what happened.
快点啦，告诉我发生什么事了.
Y'all seemed happy.
你们俩看起来很开心.
See, I can't even have a normal  conversation with you, because...
你看吧，我都没法跟你正常说话，因为...
- Hey.  - You looking for love, boy?
- 喂.  - 你在寻找真爱的吗, 帅哥?
That's what we call the Lawson workshop,  the love school.
那就是为什么我要把  劳森研讨会称为爱之学校的原因
- Is that what you're looking for?  - That's why I came to Fisk.
- 那就是你正在寻找的吗?  - 那就是我来费斯克大学的原因.
Me, too.
我也是
- I'm Carol Hammie.  - Louis Gaines.
- 我是卡罗尔 阿米耶.  - 罗伊斯 盖恩斯
Come on. Follow me.
来吧，跟着我.
You a country boy, ain't you?
你是个乡下男孩, 是吗?
He's a doctor. What does your dad do?
他是一名医生.  你爸爸是做什么的?
He's in politics.
他在政治领域工作.
You were gonna need help  finding this place anyway.
要没有人帮忙你是很难找到这个地方的
...nor can you sustain it  over a month.
...而且你也无法维持超过一个月.
- Really?  - This requires time, commitment,
- 真的吗?  - 这需要时间, 还需要有承担,
dedication, discipline and focus.
要有献身精神, 严格的纪律以及专注的注意力
And we are measuring our  accomplishments in waves, right?
而且我们得衡量我们取得的每一个阶段性的成就，对吗?
This is not a fly-by-night affair.  This doesn't happen over a week.
这不是一个能够投机取巧的事情  过去一周都没有再发生过那样的事了
This requires a fierce discipline,  which is what we've been discussing.
这需要一个我们一直以来  所探讨的严格的纪律
How do you measure these things?
我们如何来衡量这些事情呢?
We go back, and we look  at somebody like Gandhi.
我们要回头去看看像甘地那样的人
Together, we are gonna study  and examine Gandhi's techniques.
我们要一起去学习甘地的经验和技巧
What has been so effective  in South Africa, so effective in India,
为什么他在南非和印度的影响力会那么大
for his own people and others,
无论是对于他自己的人民，还是对于其他国家的人民
and we're gonna employ it  right here, in Nashville.
我们要借鉴他们的经验，而且要用在纳什维尔.
So we're gonna form an army.  You and I.
我们要组建一支部队.你们和我
This army has one weapon.  That weapon is love.
这支部队只有一种武器  那个武器就是爱
Now, I am of the... yes.
此刻，我就是... 你说.
If our only weapon is love,
如果我们唯一的武器是爱
and then their weapons  are weapons,
而他们的武器是真的武器,
- I mean, isn't that dangerous?  - Oh, you can be killed.
- 我是说，那不是很危险吗?  - 噢，你会被他们杀掉的.
If anybody's uncomfortable with that,  you know where the door is.
如果有谁不喜欢我们的主张,  你知道门在哪儿.
I understand that sounds  provocative, but it's true.
我明白那听起来充满了挑衅，但那是事实
All right, kids.  It's show time.
好了，同学们  现在是演出时间
"Function at the Junction"]
Gandhi has demonstrated for us  that the brown man,
甘地已经向我们证明了  在他们国家或者任何地方
in his native land, or anywhere  that he's being oppressed...
生活着的那些棕色人种...
...can pull himself out of segregation
...可以不再忍受脱离种族隔离制度的压迫
with patience, with persistence,
只要有无比的耐心、坚持和毅力,
with intelligence and thought,  with discipline...
运用自己智慧和思想，以及自律...
...and a bit  of a sense of humor.
...还有一点点幽默感.  我们就可以做到
You know y'all can't sit here.
你们知道你们是不可以坐在这里的
We would like to be served, please.
我们很愿意接受你的服务
This is unprecedented,  what we're talking about,
我们所谈论的事情并不是没有先例
but it needs a patience  that none of us have ever seen.
但是这需要我们有足够的耐心.
You can order food  in the colored section,
你可以去有色人种的那个区域点餐
but I'm not gonna be  serving you here.
但是在这里  我不会为你提供服务的
We are organized.  We have a leader with every group.
我们是有组织的.  我们每一个团队都设有一名领导.
We have lookouts  with pocket change
我们有负责观察和监督的人员
and the local phone numbers  for ambulances ready,
以及当地的救护车电话号码
and when one wave comes  off that lunch counter, what follows?
一旦有人在那个餐馆里遇到麻烦  接下来要做什么?
A whole 'nother wave of Negro students
其他坐在餐馆里的黑人学生
sitting at that lunch counter,  blowing their mind.
就要上前向他们陈述你们的想法
We would like  to be served, please.
请为我们提供服务，谢谢
Now, who wants to role-play?
现在，有谁愿意参与角色扮演?
Jim, I need your help over here.
吉姆，我这里需要帮助
Now, y'all know you're  not supposed to sit there.
你们都知道你们不应该坐在那里
- Attack.  - Get up, nigger! Get up!
- 攻击.  - 站起来，黑鬼，站起来!
This is an experiment.
这只是一次试验.
So do whatever it takes  to break their spirits.
所以，要尽一切可能去挫败对方的锐气
- Come on, get up, nigger.  - Use the language.
- 快点，站起来，黑鬼  - 要使用语言.
I need to hear "nigger" coming  out of your mouth.
我需要听到从你们的嘴里说出 "黑鬼" 这个词
- I need to hear "coon."  - I don't feel comfortable saying that.
- 我需要听到你们说 "coon. "(也是侮辱黑人的称谓)  - 说那个会让我感到不舒服.
You came here to get yourself prepared  and to get her prepared.
既然你来到这里，就要做好准备  也要让她做好准备
So let me hear it now.
那么，现在说给我听吧
- Nigger.  - Louder.
- 黑鬼.  - 大声点.
Say the words like you mean it.
你要让别人听起来好像你是认真的
- Nigger.  - Louder.
- 黑鬼.  - 大声点
You are a nigger!
你是个黑鬼!
You need to be sitting  in the colored seating.
你得去坐在有色人种的座位上
This is not for you,  you cannot be served here.
这里不是你待的地方  在这里你不会得到服务的
You need to do as you're told  and sit in your place.
你应该按照这位女士的吩咐  去坐在你该坐的地方
- You are a nigger.  - Make her believe it.
- 你是个黑鬼  - 要让她相信你
- I don't believe you.  - You're a nigger.
- 我不相信你  - 你是个黑鬼
You know that's where  the colored people sit.
你知道有色人种应该坐在哪里
You see these people over here?  They're in their section over here.
看到那边的那些人类吗  他们就坐在他们自己的区域里
You coon ass!  Get up, you nigger!
你个死黑鬼!  快起来，你个黑鬼!
If you want us to shop  in this establishment, make them go.
如果你想让我们在这里买东西  那就别让他们待在这里
Come on, Robert, let's go.
快点，罗伯特，我们走吧
Nigger lover, get out!
你们这对黑鬼鸳鸯, 快点出去!
- Get up, monkey. Get up!  - What is this?
- 快起来，死猴子，起来!  - 怎么回事?
Are you listening to us?
你没听到我们的话吗?
This says "whites only."
这里写着"只欢迎白人. "
Get up, nigger. Get up!
起来，黑鬼, 起来!
- Coons here?  - What are you doing here?
- 有黑鬼在这里呀?  - 你们在这里做什么呢?
- Does it say "coons?"  - "Whites only."
- 难道这里有写着 "黑鬼?"  - "只欢迎白人. "
You don't belong here with them.  This? What is this, huh?
你不属于这里. 这是什么?
- Does it say "coons" here, huh?  - What are you doing here?
- D难道这里有写着 "黑鬼?"  啊?  - 你们在这里做什么?
- Pay attention.  - No, this is whites only.
- 仔细听着.  - 不，只有白人能待在这里.
You don't belong here at all.
你们不属于这里.
What are you reading?  I didn't know niggers could read.
你在读什么呢?  我还不知道黑鬼也会阅读
What are you, stupid?  You're a nigger lover now?
你是什么玩意儿, 傻X  你们现在是一对黑鬼鸳鸯了吗?
Get up, you nigger!  Look at me!
快起来，你个死黑鬼  看着我!
- Look at me!  - What are you doing?
- 看着我!  - 你们在这里做什么??
You disrespectful monkey. Huh?
你个没教养的死猴子?
Do you understand?  You understand?
你听明白了吗? 明白了吗?
Stop it! Stop it!
住手，住手!
What do you think you're doing here?
你以为你们能在这里干嘛呢?
Get up! Get up, you nigger!  Look at me! Look at me!
起来，快起来，你个死黑鬼  看着我，看着我!
That up there or is that here?
在那上边，还是在这里?
You don't have to tell me,
你用不着告诉我,
- but you have to decide.  - I was a nigger.
- 但是你必须得做个决定.  - 我是个黑鬼.
- Go back to where you came from!  - Here, you want some coffee?
- 滚回你来的地方!  - 给你，你不是想来点咖啡吗?
...the niggers are better  off in their own schools
...黑鬼们最好滚回他们自己的学校
than they are in the white schools.
而不是待在白人的学校里.
- To serving our country.  - Serving our country.
- 为我们的国家服务.  - 为我们的国家服务.
My man.
我的兄弟.
I feel rich right now.  I like the way that tastes.
我现在觉得很富有  我喜欢这个口味.
They got no business out here.
这里没他们什么事
...better off in their  own schools than they are
...最好滚回他们自己的学校
in the white schools.
而不是待在白人的学校里.
You're all sentenced to 3O days
你们几个都被判定....
- in the countyjail.  - What?
- 在郡监狱服刑30天.  - 什么?
Bailiff, get these  niggers out of here.
法警, 把这些黑鬼带离这里
Something special  is going on down here, Dad.
这里发生了一些很特别的事情，爸爸
What's so special about  another colored man in jail?
对于一个进了监狱的有色人种可言  还能有什么特别的事?
What you doing  with my hard earned money, Pop?
你究竟在拿老子辛辛苦苦赚来的钱  搞虾米灰机?
Are you even in school?
你还在学校吗?
I'm trying to change  the way Negroes...
我是在试着改变黑鬼的...
You're breaking the law.
你违法了法律.
That judge just sentenced you  to 3O days in the county workhouse.
那个法官刚刚才宣判你去郡教养所服刑30天.
You fixing to get killed.
在那里你会死的
If I can't sit at any  lunch counter I want,
如果我都无法坐在任何我想坐的餐馆里,
then I might as well be dead.
那么我还不如死了算了.
- We're fighting for our rights.  - Rights?
- 我们在为我们的权利而奋斗.  - 权利?
- What are you talking about?  - We're trying to change
- 你究竟是说什么呢?  - 我们在试着改变
the nation's consciousness  toward the American Negro.
这个国家的民众对待黑鬼的态度和意识.
Them postcards you've been sending me?
那你寄给我的那些明信片是怎么回事?
- You're a damn liar.  - I have been in school.
- 你就是该死的谎话精.  - 我一直在学校.
Who do you think you're talking to?
你以为你是在跟谁说话呢?
I brought you into this world,  I can take you out of it.
是我把你带到了这个世界上  我也一样可以带你离开那里
- Y'all been able to talk to him?  - Talk to who?
- 你们一直跟他有联络?  - 谁?
- Louis.  - Yeah, we talk to him.
- 路易斯  - 对
Said he's joined something  called the "Freedom Riders,"
他说他参加了一个什么东东  叫什么“自由骑士”
whatever the hell  that's supposed to mean.
搞不明白那究竟是个什么意思
You gonna see him?
你要去看他吗?
I been fixing to trying to see him.
我一直想要去看他
Every time I do,  Cecil get all riled up.
但是每次我一提这茬儿  塞西尔就跟我发火
So I don't know when  that's gonna happen.
所以我也不晓得我究竟什么时候才能去看他
"Fixing to trying."  See, that's the problem.
"试着想要.... "  你看，这就是问题所在
You got to stop trying,  and you just got to do it.
想去就去，别老是想来想去的
He take you  to the White House yet?
他有没有带你去过白宫?
No. Cecil say we're going soon.
没有，塞西尔说我们很快就会去了
"Cecil say, Cecil say."
"塞西尔说，塞西尔说. "
Four years. That's what makes  you a little bit gullible, darling.
都四年了.你还是那么容易就相信他说的话，亲爱的
I don't understand.  I don't understand why he can't
我不明白.  我也不明白为什么他就不能....
- get the president to do something.  - See, Gina, that's your problem.
- ...让总统干点啥.  - 你看，吉娜，这就是你的问题所在.
You just say stupid stuff.
你就知道说这些傻乎乎的屁话
President got more to do than be  thinking about Louis' foolishness.
总统有那么多的事要做  那里有功夫去理会路易斯的那点愚蠢的破事
You know,  why don't you just shut up?
为什么你就不能干脆闭上嘴?
It's just a mess.  Be nice.
现在遇上这么糟心的事儿  你就不能表现得友好一点吗.
Who told you  you could tell me to shut up?
谁跟你说了你可以让我闭嘴的?
- Well...  You...  - Go get me a drink.
- 嗯... 你..  - 去给我拿点喝的来.
I want some scotch.
我要喝点儿苏格兰威士忌
Well, I personally think Louis is  gonna get every one of us killed.
我个人的想法是路易斯会  把我们大家都害死的
They coming to get us.  They coming to get us.
他们会来抓我们的.  他们会来抓我们的.
He crazy like his mama.
他就跟他妈妈一样疯狂
I meant it in a good way.
我是说，在好的方面.
I'm sorry!  I'm sorry.
对不起! 对不起
Get back over here.
回来这里啦.
Let me get your ass.
我还是跟这你们进去吧
I received also a wire from  President Eisenhower, which says...
我收到了艾森豪威尔总统的一个电报  上面说...
The president lives  at the White House
总统会住在白宫
until the moment the next one  is sworn in.
一直到下一位总统宣誓就职
So the staff has exactly two hours
所以，在总统的就职典礼进行期间
during the inauguration ceremony,  to move the old president out
员工只有两个小时的时间  要把上一任总统的东西搬出去
and move the new one in.
然后再把新任总统的东西搬进来.
They say  this new white boy's smooth.
他们说，这个新来的白人小子很圆滑
I just need to get my  butt home to Gloria.
我只想快点回家找格罗瑞亚
'Cause these hours,  they're killing us.
忙活这半天累得快要死了
How's your boy doing, Cecil?
你儿子怎么样了, 塞西尔?
Gentlemen, the president's arriving.
先生们, 总统到了.
- OK.  - Where shall we start?
- 好的  - 我们要从哪儿开始?
I'm not sure.  This end, maybe over there?
我也不确定  也许我们从那边开始?
- Thank you.  - Right this way, Mr. President.
- 谢谢  - 请这边走，总统先生
- Hello, everyone.  - Mr. President.
- 大家好  - 总统先生
I am thrilled to be  working with all of you
能和你们大家一起共事让我很激动
over the next four years.
在接下来的四年里
Eight years, Jack.
是八年，杰克
Well, you see who wears  the pants around here.
好吧，你们会看到谁会在这里当家
I'm not gonna remember any  of your names, but I'm gonna try.
我不一定能记住你们每一位的姓名  但是我会试试看的
Jessie. It's a good thing you're here  'cause I'm gonna forget.
杰西. 你在这里会很好  因为我会忘记的
- Thank you. This is Lorraine.  - Pleasure to meet you.
- 谢谢你. 这位是罗琳.  - 很荣幸见到你.
- Mr. President.  - How are you, James?
- 总统先生  - 你好，詹姆斯先生?
- Carter.  - Pleasure, Mr. President.
- 卡特.  - 很荣幸见到你，总统先生.
- Carter.  - This is Cecil.
- 卡特.  - 这位是塞西尔.
- Pleasure to meet you, Mr. President.  - How are you?
- 很荣幸见到你，总统先生.  - 你好?
- William.  - Mrs. Kennedy.
- 威廉.  - 肯尼迪夫人.
- Greg.  - How are you?
- 格雷格.  - 你好?
Winslow.
温斯洛.
I got it. She's all right.
我拣起来了，她没事.
Pleasure to meet you,  Miss Caroline.
很高兴见到你，卡罗琳小姐.
- Miles.  - Miles.
- 迈尔斯.  - 迈尔斯.
What's that on your breath,  Gloria? Stop, OK. Stop.
你的呼吸里是什么味道,  格罗瑞亚? 住手，好吗，住手.
- What's that?  - Baby, that's gin.
- 那是什么?  - 宝贝，那是杜松子酒的味道.
- I can smell it from here.  - It said "Addison's disease."
- 我从这里都可以闻得出来  - 那叫作阿狄森氏病
Stop. Stop it, will you stop?
住手，住手啦，你能住手嘛?
Did you take Charlie  to the dentist today?
你今天有没有带查理去看牙医?
Somebody at the White House  got Addison's disease?
在白宫有人得了阿狄森氏病?
No, I did not take Charlie  to the dentist today.
没有，我今天没有带查理去看牙医.
And what you asking me about it for?  You never home.
而且，你问那些做什么?  你又从来不在家.
Now you gonna act like you gonna  take Charlie to the dentist?
你问这个就好像你会带查理去看牙医一样
You ain't never here.  I don't know how you gonna take him.
你从来都不会在家.  我都不知道你要怎么样带他们去
His teeth fall out,  waiting on you to take him.
他的牙齿脱落了  他等着你带他去看牙医呢.
Just go to bed, Gloria.  I'll take him tomorrow.
快睡觉吧，格罗瑞亚  我明天会带他去
How many pairs of shoes  does she have?
她究竟有多少双鞋子呀?
I said, how many pairs of shoes  does Mrs. Jackie Kennedy have?
我问你呢，杰奎琳·肯尼迪夫人究竟有多少双鞋子呀?
How the hell do I know?
我他妈的怎么知道?
You're in that 0l' White House  day and night.
你不是一天到晚都待在白宫里吗.
Thought you knew everything.
我还以为你无所不知呢.
Coming in,  trying to tell me what to do.
可你就会一进家门  告诉我我应该做什么
Worried about me drinking.
担心我是不是喝酒了.
You ought to be worried  about your house.
塞西尔，你应该多操心自己家里的事
Our boy's in jail, Cecil.
我们的儿子还在监狱里呢.
Our boy's in jail,  and you can't come home.
我们的儿子在监狱里  可你都不能回家
You... You don't see I'm here,  trying to talk to you?
你... 你没看到我正在试着跟你谈话吗?
I bet you wish I spoke French,  just like Jackie.
我敢打赌你肯定希望我能说法语  就像杰奎琳一样.
Jackie Kennedy.
杰奎琳 肯尼迪
Que sera, sera.
该怎样, 就怎样.（法语）
You like that?
你喜欢这样?
You like the way she talk?
你喜欢她说话的方式吗?
Cecil,  you hear me talking to you.
塞西尔，你听没听到我在跟你说话呢
You ain't asleep.
你根本就没睡着.
Bobby told the president
鲍比告诉总统说
they shouldn't be worried about  the Negro sit-ins.
他们不应该担心那些黑鬼静坐示威的事
Polls show the US  does not support civil rights.
民意调查显示美国的民权问题始终没有得到改善.
Told you that white boy was smooth.  A little too smooth for my money.
我跟你说过那个白人男孩（总统）很圆滑  依我看来他有点太狡猾了
- Hey, Cecil, how's your boy doing?  - Out of jail, says he's back in school,
- 喂，塞西尔，你儿子怎么样了?  - 已经出狱了，他说他已经回去学校了,
but I think he's doing  that freedom riding thing.
但我觉得他还在从事  他那个什么自由骑士的事儿
How's Gloria doing  with that drinking?
格罗瑞亚还在喝酒吗?
She's hanging-
还在断断续续地喝.
They say that cat  that's playing is a big deal.
他们说那个家伙的演奏非常棒
- Pablo Casals, world famous.  - Course he's world famous.
- 帕布罗·卡萨尔斯，在全世界都很有名  - 他当然很有名啦.
You think Mrs. Kennedy  is gonna have, uh...
你觉得肯尼迪夫人会，嗯 ...
some backwoods country fiddle  band playing out there for her?
让什么不知名的小人物来这里为她演奏小提琴?
- Man.  - Why don't you start a band?
- 得啦.  - 为什么你不整一个乐队?
Maybe you can go out there, too.
也许你也可以出去那里演奏呢
You know what, in fact,  let's all start a band.
你知道吗，事实上  我们可以一起组建一个乐队
I'll play the bongos.  What about you?
我会弹奏小手鼓.  你准备弹奏什么?
I play a mean... skin flute.
我会吹奏长笛  （skin flute也有口交的意思）.
- ♪ Babalu.  - Casals is a righteous soul.
- # 巴巴鲁.  - 卡萨尔斯是一个正直的人.
He refuses to play in any country  that recognizes Franco's regime.
他拒绝去任何一个承认佛朗哥政权的国家演奏  （弗朗西斯科佛朗哥是西班牙的独裁领袖）
Who's Franco?
佛朗哥是谁?
- Forget it, man.  - Huh?
- 当我没说.  - 嗯?
Forget it. You're ignorant.
当我没说，你太无知了.
Carol, are you tired?
卡萝尔, 你累了吗?
You just want me to put my head  on your shoulder.
你是不是想让我靠在你肩膀上
What wrong with that?
那有什么不对吗?
I'm not putting my head  on your shoulder.
我才不会靠在你的肩膀上啦.
You can.
你当然可以的
Ever been  on a freedom bus before?
以前从没坐过自由巴士?
- No, it's my first time.  - No?
- 没有，这是我第一次乘坐.  - 没有吗?
- How's your boyfriend feel about that?  - My boyfriend?
- 你男朋友对此有何看法?  - 我男朋友?
Yeah. I mean,  this must upset him, right?
嗯，我是说  这会惹他不开心吧，对吗?
You being on this bus down here.
你现在坐在这辆巴士上.
- I don't have a boyfriend.  - You don't have a boyfriend?
- 我没有男朋友  - 你没男朋友?
How do you not have a boyfriend?
你怎么可能没有男朋友?
- You want some peanuts?  - No, thank you.
- 要不要吃点花生?  - 不要了，谢谢
- You like peanuts or...?  - I don't like peanuts.
- 你喜欢吃花生还是...?  - 我不喜欢花生.
- I'm too hot to eat.  - Hey, can I have some of those?
- 我不能吃东西.  - 喂，我可以吃点儿吗?
- Long bus ride.  - OK.
- 这是一次长途旅行.  - 好的.
Louis, what is that?
路易斯，那是什么?
- It's a cross. It's a cross.  - Driver, turn! Turn the bus!
- 那是一个十字架. 那是一个十字架.  - 司机，转弯，快转弯
Oh, shit.
噢，靠.
Niggers, get out here!
黑鬼们，滚出来!
Nigger, go home! Nigger, go home!
黑鬼，滚回家吧, 黑鬼，滚回家吧!
Oh, my God.  Everybody out!
噢，上帝呀. 大家都出去
"In an old house in Paris
在巴黎的一所外面盖满了...
that was covered with vines...
葡萄藤的老房子里...
...lived 12 little girls  in two straight lines.
...住着12位小女孩
The smallest one  was Madeline."
其中最小的那一位叫玛德琳
- Like Caroline.  - Mm-hm.
- 就像卡罗琳吗.  - 嗯
"She was not afraid of mice."
她一点都不害怕老鼠
Why do people ride  in the freedom bus?
为什么人们要乘坐那辆自由巴士呢?
Uncle Bobby told my daddy
鲍比叔叔告诉我爸爸说
that the freedom bus  exploded today.
今天有一辆自由巴士爆炸了
I can't tell you  if I walked off the bus
我不能告诉你我是如何离开那辆巴士的
or if I crawled off  or if someone pulled me off.
是我自己从车里爬出来的  还是有人拉我出来的
I didn't know if my boy  was dead or alive.
我不知道我儿子是否还活着
When I got off the bus,  a man came up to me,
当我从那辆车里出来的时候  一个男人向我走了过来
and I'm coughing and strangling,
当时我正在剧烈咳嗽，几乎要窒息而死了
and he said, "Boy, you all right?"
然后我听到他说, "孩子，你没事吗?"
And I nodded my head,  and the next thing I knew,
我点了点头  我所知道的下一件事就是
I was on the ground.
我躺在地上
He had hit me with a baseball bat.
他在用一个棒球棒用力地打我.
Hello.
你好.
Hi, Dad.  I'm in Mississippi.
嗨，爸爸.  我现在在密西西比.
I thought you was in Alabama.
我还以为你在阿拉巴马.
We spent two weeks in jail  there, now we're in Mississippi.
我们在那里的监狱里待了两周  现在我们在密西西比.
I want you to listen  to me, Louis.
我希望你能听我说，路易斯.
I want you to come home.
我希望你能回家
I know we ain't seen eye to eye,
我知道我们对一些事情的看法有分歧
but your mama,  she wants you home.
但是你妈妈她，  她很想你能回家
- They're keeping me.  - How long?
- 他们扣留了我.  - 要多久?
- Where is he?  - I don't know.
- 他在哪儿?  - 我不知道.
They said three months.
他们说大概要三个月.
When I get out,  I'm gonna take another ride.
等我出去的时候  我会开始另一次自由之旅.
- What are you talking about?  - What's he saying?
- 你在说什么呀?  - 他怎么说?
Let me talk to him.  Give me that phone.
让我跟他说，把电话给我.
It is my right to ride that bus.  That is my legal right.
搭乘那辆巴士，那是我的权利  那是我的合法权利
I will exercise my rights  as an American citizen.
作为一名美国公民，我要运用我的权利
American citizen.  What you talking about?
美国公民.  你说什么呐?
You know what  they're gonna do to you?
你知道他们会如何对待你吗?
They're gonna lynch you
他们会将你处以私刑
and then they're gonna throw  your little ass in the river.
他们会把你扔进河里
They're gonna kill you.
他们会杀了你
Ma, then they're just  gonna have to kill me.
妈妈，那么他们起码得杀了我，才能阻止我
...Negro  and white in Birmingham
...伯明翰的黑鬼和白人
have been building up  to scenes with clashes, like this.
一直在制造类似的此种冲突.
The situation was perilously  close to an explosion.
现在的情形非常严峻，几乎要引发一次暴动了
Arrests were made in mass lots.
警方已经拘捕了大量的肇事人员.
Everyone charged  with the same offense...
并且所有都因为相同的原因遭到了起诉...
Here you are, Mr. President.
给你，总统先生.
I'll wait for your signature.
我会等你签完字.
City police were  carrying out their pledge
城市警察已经在着手扩大监狱的容量
to fill their jails to  capacity if necessary.
以备不时之需
They are acting  according to the wishes...
他们这样做的目的是为了迎合...的意愿...
I don't know what country  I'm looking at.
我都不知道我现在看到的  这个究竟是什么国家
...tone of the city for many years.
...这种论调已经持续了许多年
Get off! Get off!
出去，出去!
Residents here  have taken to the streets
在阿拉巴马州伯明翰市,
in Birmingham, Alabama,  to bring attention to their efforts
住在这里的人们走上街头  去关注他们为了对抗美国政府
against the segregation  of black Americans.
对于美国黑人所实施的种族隔离制度所作出的努力
This is following earlier boycotts  in Birmingham to pressure...
这是早些时候发生在伯明翰的  为了向....施压的抵抗示威活动...
Hey, Louis, man, that little  nigga might be onto something.
路易斯，那个小黑鬼可能做了点儿什么事吧
Stop calling him a nigga,  'cause he ain't no nigga.
不许再叫他黑鬼,  因为他不是黑鬼.
What's wrong, baby?
有什么问题嘛，宝贝?
- What's wrong with me is this.  - What are you talking about?
- 就是这个问题.  - 你说什么呢?
This is what's wrong with me.  This is wrong. This is wrong.
那就是问题所在  那是不对的，那是不对的.
- We ain't been wrong yet.  - I can't do this to Cecil.
- 我们也没有做错什么.  - 我不能这么对待塞西尔.
We ain't doing it to Cecil.  I'm doing it to you.
我们怎么做又不是冲着塞西尔  我这么做是为了你
I want you out of my house.
我希望你能离开我的房子.
Why do you think God brought us  next to each other each day?
那你觉得为什么上帝  会让我们俩每天都待在一起
- God ain't got nothing to do with this.  - He put you right next door to me.
- 这跟上帝一点儿关系都没有.  - 是他让你住在了我的隔壁.
You always talking about how  lonely you are without Cecil
你不是总在说塞西尔待在白宫的时候  你有多么多么孤独和寂寞...
being at the White House,  and you need a man that can
而且你需要一个男人能像我一样..
appreciate the love and the  woman that you are, like I do.
欣赏你，并且感激你所付出的爱...
I want your number-running  ass up out of my house,
我希望你这快点把你的赌棍屁股挪出我家门
off of my sofa right now.
马上从我的沙发上起来.
I'm... I'm through.  I told you.
我... 我们俩结束了.  我已经告诉你了.
Let me make  a demonstration for you.
让我来证明给你看.
Don't come here with  this bullshit crazy talk.
别再来这里发表你的那些狗屁演说
- It's not.  - Some more of this...
- 不是那个了.  - 比那个更扯...
This is you, right? You got  your direction that you move in.
这个是你, 对吗?  你正在朝着你的方向前进.
- What you doing with my hangers?  - This is you, and this is me.
- 你拿我的衣架瞎搞什么呢?  - 这一个是你, 这一个是我.
Now, we seem like we don't fit at all.  We just crash into each other.
现在，我们看上去好像完全不合拍  我们只是不小心碰到了一起
But then when  you align things properly,
可是接下来 我们开始慢慢回到了正确的位置上
like God putting you  next door to me,
就像上帝安排你住在了我的隔壁一样
everything kind of works out.
所有的事看起来都有了转机.
And even if you slow down,  I got you.
即使你的热情减退了，我也能明白你的心意
You need to get your yellow  ass up out of my house.
抬起你的脏屁股，滚出我的房子
- We need each other.  - What I need is my husband.
- 我们需要彼此  - 我需要的是我的丈夫.
And not to be laying up here  in the gutter with you.
而不是和你待在破贫民窟里
On average, how many pills do  you think I take a day, Cecil?
就平均而言，你觉得我一天大概  要吃多少药，塞西尔?
About... 103, sir.
差不多... 103, 先生.
- Help me up.  - Mr. President.
- 扶我起来.  - 总统先生.
I know your son is a Freedom Rider.
我知道你儿子是一名自由骑士.
He's in prison right now in Birmingham  with Martin Luther King.
此刻他正和马丁.路德.金待在伯明翰的监狱里
Do you, uh...
你...
...you know how he is, sir?
...你知道他怎么样吗, 先生?
I'm guessing he's pretty beat up,  but based on his record,
我猜他应该被打得够呛  但是根据他的记录来看
he must be used to it.
他肯定早已经习惯了
Cecil, he's been arrested 16 times  over the past two years.
塞西尔, 过去两年里他已经被逮捕过16次了.
Yes, sir.
是的，先生.
- Will that be all, sir?  - That's it.
- 没事了吗, 先生?  - 就这样吧.
You know, I never understood
你知道，我以前一直都不明白
what you all really went through...
你们究竟都经历过什么...
...until I saw that.
...直到我看到了那个.
My brother says these kids have...
我兄弟说那些孩子们...
...changed his heart.
...改变了他的心意.
They've changed mine, too.
他们也改变了我的
The fires of discord are burning  in every city North and South,
失望和纷争之火在  北部以及南部的每座城市燃烧
where legal remedies  are not at hand.
在南北方没有法律补救措施的地方燃烧。
Redress is sought in the streets,
人们上街示威、游行、抗议，
in demonstrations,  parades and protests.
以此来寻求补救之法....
I am therefore  asking the Congress
因此，我要求
to enact legislation
国会立法
giving all Americans the right  to be served in facilities
赋予所有美国人在宾馆、
which are open to the public.
餐厅、剧场、...
Hotels, restaurants, theaters,
零售店以及类似公共场
retail stores  and similar establishments.
享受服务的权利。
This seems to me to be  an elementary right.
这在我看来是一项基本权利.
Its denial is  an arbitrary indignity
对这项基本权利的剥夺是恣意损害公民尊严的行为
that no American in 1963  should have to endure, but many do.
是1963年的美国人不应当被迫容忍的行为  但有许多人却在容忍
A great change is at hand.
一场重大变革的变革即将到来，
And our task, our obligation,  is to make that revolution,
而我们的任务、我们的义务是使这场革命  这场变革对于所有人都是
that change,  peaceful and constructive for all.
和平的和具有建设性的
Those who do nothing are  inviting shame as well as violence...
无所作为者是在自取耻辱和鼓励暴力...
Hey. Hey, Cecil.  Cecil, what's wrong?
喂，塞西尔  塞西尔，怎么了?
Cecil?
塞西尔?
They blew his...
他们打中了他...
...head off.
...的头.
- Who are you talking about?  - Kennedy.
- 你说的是谁呀?  - 肯尼迪.
President Kennedy was shot
肯尼迪总统被枪击了
as he drove from Dallas airport  to downtown Dallas...
当他乘车从达拉斯机场前往达拉斯市中心时...
They killed him.
他们杀了他.
Governor Connally of Texas  in the car with him was also shot.
和他同乘一辆车的时任德州州长康纳利  也同时遭到枪击
It is reported that  three bullets rang out.
据报道称，现场一共有三发子弹
A Secret Serviceman has been...
一位前海军陆战队员...
They killed our man.
他们杀死了我们的老大.
"He's dead." Whether he  referred to President Kennedy or not
"他死了. " 他是否与肯尼迪总统有关联
is not yet known.
目前还不得而知
The president, cradled in the  arms of his wife, Mrs. Kennedy,
总统倒在她的妻子肯尼迪夫人的怀中
was carried to an ambulance  and the car rushed
直到救护车前来将他们带离现场
to Parkland Hospital outside Dallas...
前往达拉斯城外的帕克兰纪念医院...
Mrs. Kennedy refused  to change her clothes,
肯尼迪夫人拒绝更换她的服装
so that everybody could see  what they did to her husband.
因此，所有的人都可以看到  他们对她的丈夫所做的事
The last time  I saw that much blood
我最后一次见到那么多的血
was the day my daddy was killed.
是在我爸爸被杀害的那一天.
Please tell me how I could help you.
请告诉我要如何才能帮到你.
Ma, what you doing?
妈妈，你在干嘛
Here. Want you to take this box  and put it in the basement.
给你，我想让你把这个盒子带到地下室去
- Make sure you label it "trophies."  - This is Louis' stuff, Ma.
- 要记得在上面贴上“奖杯”的标签  - 这是路易斯的东西，妈妈
You know he gonna be pissed.
你知道你这么做会惹恼他的
I don't care nothing about  Louis being pissed.
我才不在乎路易斯是不是会被惹恼.
I'm the one pissed.  He ain't been here in three years.
现在我才是被惹恼的那个人  三年来他从未回来过这里
Why you pissed, Mama?
你生什么气呢，妈妈?
And don't put that next  to myjarred okra either.
也不要把那个东西放在我的秋葵罐子边上
Ain't nobody trying to smell  that stankin' okra.
才没有人乐意闻那个臭得要命的秋葵呢
And when you come back, I want  you to get me some fish food.
你回来的时候，帮我带一点新鲜的食物
Look what the president...
看看总统...
...Mrs. Kennedy gave me.
...这是肯尼迪夫人送给我的.
Belonged to the president.
这是属于肯尼迪总统的.
Gloria...
格罗瑞亚...
President was killed.
总统被杀害了.
I'm really sorry about the president.
关于总统的事，我很遗憾
I really am.
我真的很遗憾.
But you and that White House  can kiss my ass.
但是你和那个白宫跟我一毛钱关系都没有
I don't care what  goes on in that house.
我才不在乎那所房子里发生的事.
I care about what goes on in this house.
我在乎的是这所房子里发生的事
"I'll Close My Eyes"]
I knew that Gloria had been  unhappy for some time now.
我知道格罗瑞亚最近一段时间  一直都很不开心
I knew that's probably  why she drank.
我知道那也许就是她喝酒的原因
She wanted me to get along  better with Louis.
她希望我跟路易斯能相处得更好一点
I didn't know how.
可是我不知道应该怎么做
I couldn't.
而且我也做不到
I could cut back them  long hours at the White House.
我可以减少待在白宫的时间.
And I did just that.
而且我也尽量在那么做
How many pairs of shoes she got?
她有多少双鞋子?
She got about... 125.
她大概有... 125双吧.
- A hundred twenty-five pairs of shoes?  - Yeah.
- 125双鞋子?  - 是的.
Put them in a line from the blacks  all the way to the whites.
要让黑人和白人之间站成一排
And I'll tell you what. Next time  there's a light on in an empty room,
我告诉你.下一次如果再让我发现  房间里没人还开着灯
I will fire every sorry son of a bitch  in this house. I mean it, Cecil!
我会开除这个房子里的不负责任的婊子养的  我是认真的，塞西尔
Go back to Texas and run the country  from a dirt shack if I have to.
如果有必要的话，我会回去德州从一个肮脏的  小棚屋开始着手管理这个国家
Is that what you want?
那是你所希望的吗?
Who do you think pays the  goddamned bills around here?
你觉得是谁在这里支付这些该死的账单?
Idon%,butyou  know what I mean.
我才不会呢，但是你明白我的意思
Yes, sir.
是的，先生.
Oh, yeah, I almost forgot.
噢，对，我差点忘了
Lady Bird and I want you to have this.
约翰逊夫人和我希望你收下这个
- Matches your eyes.  - Thank you, sir.
- 很衬你的眼睛.  - 谢谢你，总统先生.
- Get it, Gloria.  - Do it, baby.
- 很好，格罗瑞亚  - 快点啦 ,宝贝.
Swim it! Go ahead, Gloria.
摇摆两下，格罗瑞亚.
- I see you, baby.  - You see me, babe? Put it on.
- 我看到你了，宝贝.  - 你看到我了，宝贝, 快穿上.
Paughs]
Get it, Gloria.
很好，格罗瑞亚.
- Now that's what I'm talking about.  - Get it, girl! Shake it out! Get it!
- 那才是我说的嘛.  - 你们做到了，摇起来!
Negro! Get out here.
黑鬼! 滚出这里.
Back there stinking up  my bathroom.
把我的洗手间弄得臭哄哄的.
- Oh, Lord.  - Oh, Lord.
- 噢，上帝呀  - 噢，上帝呀
What you doing?
你干嘛呢?
Hey! Whoo!
哇噢!
What?
搞什么?
Get you some!
给你来一点!
- You know.  - That's your friend.
- 你知道.  - 那是你的朋友.
Give me my wig!  What's wrong with you?!
把我的假发还给我!  你有毛病啊?!
- This my good wig!  - Oh, shit!
- 那是我最好的假发!  - 噢，我靠!
- Sit down.  - We got the spades up.
- 坐下.  - 我们拿到黑桃了（不晓得啥游戏）.
Brotherjust handling his business.
哥们刚处理完他的事情
He can still do the splits,  I'll tell you.
他仍然可以来个劈叉  我来告诉你吧
James told me  that Dr. King told the president
詹姆斯跟我我说，金博士告诉总统...  （马丁.路德.金）
that we would be going to the streets  down South for our right to vote.
我们要去街上投选票了.
- Didn't you, baby?  - What?
- 是不是你说的，宝贝?  - 什么?
Didn't you tell me  that Dr. King told the president
你是不是跟我说了那个金博士告诉总统
that we was going down South  for our right to vote?
我们要去街上投选票了.?
- I ain't make that up.  - Is that what you heard?
- 那不是我编造的吧.  - 你真的听他们那么说来着?
That Dr. King ain't no joke,  with his little militant ass.
那个金博士可不会端着他的  那个好斗的小屁股开玩笑
- She talking too damned much.  - Well, sound like somebody talking.
- 她他妈的说得多了.  - 听起来好像是某个人在讲话
Shut up.
闭嘴.
- Leave my bird alone.  - Well, you know them three kids
- 别欺负我的小鸟.  - 你知道有三个孩子
got killed down there, trying to get  colored folks registered to vote.
在那里被杀害了,  所以他们想让黑人去参加投票
That's why I didn't want  Louis to go down there.
那就是为什么我不想路易斯去那儿的原因
That's what I was  trying to tell you.
那也是我一直想要告诉你的事
You shouldn't have  sent him down there.
你当时就不应该让他去那里
- I know.  - He is down there now,
- 我知道  - 但是现在,他已经在那里了
and there ain't nothing  we can do about it.
而且我们现在对此也无能为力.
The only reason  the president sent the FBI
总统之所以会派遣FBI  唯一原因就是..
is 'cause two of them were white.
他们两个都是白人.
- Now who told you that?  - Yeah, who told her that?
- 那又是谁告诉你的?  - 对啊，那是谁告诉她的?
It was in one of them colored newspapers  from Baltimore. That all right with you?
那是我从巴尔的摩的一张黑人报纸上看到的  你满意了吗
See, she getting smart now.
你瞧，她现在变聪明了
Honey, you think the president  ought to do something
亲爱的, 你觉得总统是不是应该
- about the Voting Rights bill?  - That ain't the trump.
- 就选举权法案做点儿什么?  - 那又不是王牌.
President Johnson  just passed the greatest piece
约翰逊总统刚刚从通过了一项..
of civil rights legislation  since Lincoln freed the slaves.
自林肯总统废除奴隶制以来  最大的民权法案
It's gonna be very difficult to  pass another bill anytime soon.
要在如此短的时间内通过  另外一项法案肯定会非常困难
- That's it.  - You see how my wife quizzes me?
- 就是那么回事  - 你们看到我老婆是如何盘问我的了吧?
- I get it every day.  - Only, you got to know
- 我每天都接受这种盘问.  - 但是你必须要知道
how much to say,  when you cross the line.
什么能说什么不能说...  一定不能越界.
You deal with your woman,  I'll deal with mine.
你处理好你老婆的事  我来处理我老婆的事
At least you tell your wife  what's going on over there.
最起码你会告诉你老婆  那里究竟发生了什么事
- A!  - Aces!  - Damn!
- 靠!
Can't be a king  in your own castle.
可惜你在你自己的城堡里都不能称王
You hit the strip joint,  that's what I say.
！@#￥%……&打扑克的说法,  我早就跟你说了
Hey, uh, Glo. Did you hear about  your neighbor, Howard?
喂，格罗瑞亚，  你有没有听说过你的邻居霍华德
Guy down on 8th Street,  caught him in bed with his wife.
他跟一个住在8街的女人厮混的时候  被她的男人逮了个正着
Shot him dead.
然后...头部中了抢.
- Shot him in the back.  - That's it. That's all of it.
- 是从他后面开枪的.  - 得了，别再说了.
I don't know, maybe he got  what he deserved.
我不知道，也许那是他自己作的.
You sorry sap asses  got to realize
你们这些傻货们应该要意识到
the Negro ain't gonna take it no more.
黑鬼不能在继续这样下去了
This entire country is a tinderbox.
现在整个国家到处危机四伏
Goddamn tinderbox of nigger rage  just waiting to explode!
那些该死的怒火中烧的黑鬼们随时都会爆发
Now, I want you all  to get on the phone,
现在, 我希望你们全部都待在电话边上
call the NAACP, CORE  and whoever else
打电话给有色人种促进协会，种族平等大会等等
will listen to your sorry asses
总之就是找那些能听得进去你们说话的组织
and help me keep them Negroes  off the street.
帮助我把那些黑鬼们从街上弄走
Buck, I smell your ass from here!  What the hell are you waiting for?!
巴克, 我闻到你的臭屁股的味儿了!  你他奶奶的还在等什么呢?!
Jesus Christ.
上帝呀
Cecil, get me some of  that goddamned prune juice.
塞西尔，给我拿点儿该死的西梅汁来.
I'm not sure what to make  of Malcolm X.
我拿不定主意究竟该拿那个  马尔科姆.艾克斯怎么办（美国黑人领袖）
I know what to make of him.
我知道他究竟在搞什么
Got a better plan  in place than Dr. King.
他有一个比马丁路德金更好的计划
If someone puts their hands on  you, put them in the cemetery.
如果有人将他们的手伸向你  那么就送他们进墓地里吧
- That a better plan?  - Ooh, We fixin' to go.
- 那就是所谓的更好的计划?  - 我们准备要走了.
Bye, Claramay.
拜,凯拉美.
- Good night.  - Good night.
- 晚安.  - 晚安.
I mean...
我是说...
You just mad 'cause he was  talking about your daddy.
你生气是因为他提到了你爸爸，是吗
What?
什么?
He was saying all that  stuff about house Negroes.
他提到了很多有关做屋内服务的黑鬼的问题
I saw you get mad.
我看到你生气了.
My dad is not a house Negro.
我爸爸不是做屋内服务的黑鬼.
- He a butler, ain't he?  - Don't talk about my dad.
- 他是个男仆, 不是吗?  - 别跟我提我爸.
I don't talk about your dad,  all right?
我也没提你爸，对吗?
That's 'cause my daddy's  proud of what I'm doing.
那是因为我所做的一切  我爸爸都会觉得很骄傲
You all right?
你没事吧?
Everybody went to church to  raise money for the kids down in Selma.
在塞尔玛市,所有人都前往教堂为孩子们筹款
But I didn't go. I wasn't gonna give  money to pay for my son to be killed.
但是我没有去. 我不想把钱捐给他们  好让他们害死我儿子
Once again, them kids got beat.
那些孩子们又一次失败了.
This one was so bad that the press  called it "Bloody Sunday."
这是一次惨痛的事件，新闻报道将之称为 "血色星期天"
They barely left Selma.
他们只有少数几个人塞尔玛市  （参见1961年的塞尔玛大桥事件）
They marched in small groups  through the city of Selma
一个小型的游行队伍穿过塞尔玛市中心
- and were not stopped...  - ...mortars and rockets...
- 没有被阻止...  - ... 迫击炮和火箭筒...
...can pound Con Thien  around the clock
...在对康天进行日以继夜地  （越南美军基地）
with devastating effect.
进行毁灭性的炮火打击.
And our ground troops  cannot go into...
我们的地面部队无法进入...
...it was a different story.
...这是一个完全不同的故事.
Mounted sheriff's deputies  helped to break up the column.
骑警协助驱散游行的人群.
Once the line was broken...
游行队伍曾一度被冲散...
How are your boys, Cecil?
你的儿子们怎么样，塞西尔?
I don't know how my oldest is,  Mr. President.
我不太了解我大儿子的情况,  总统先生.
I believe he might  be in Selma.
我相信他可能也在塞尔玛市
And, you know,  sometime I feel like
而且，你知道  有时候我觉得
we're living in  two different worlds.
我跟他，就好像生活在  截然不同的两个世界里
Just want to keep him safe.
我只是希望他能安然无恙
...marchers were  treated for tear gas burns,
...游行队伍被催泪瓦斯烧伤,
open wounds and broken bones.
裸露的伤口和骨折
One hospital treated...
被送去医院进行治疗...
Every American citizen  must have an equal right to vote.
每一个美国公民都有平等的权利去投票
Yet the harsh fact is that  in many places in this country,
尽管，在这个国家的很多地方  还存在着严峻的不公的事实
men and women  are kept from voting
人们无法进行投票
simply because they are Negroes.
其原因仅仅是因为他们是黑鬼.
"Negroes?"
"黑鬼?"
Since when did he start  calling us Negroes?
他是从什么时候开始叫我们黑鬼的?
That nigger uses the word  "nigger" more than I use it.
那个黑鬼用这个词的频率比我还高
But really it's all of us...
但是说真的，我们所有人...
...who must overcome  the crippling legacy
...必须要解决这一极其不公正的....
of bigotry and injustice.
造成了严重后果的历史遗留问题
And we shall overcome.
我们一定会做到的.
First,  a barrage of cover fire,
起初是接二连三的火力压制,
and then a charge across the street.
发起了一次冲锋.
The Marines moved out from  the fortified Army compound
海军陆战队开始
blitzed by the original attack.
进行闪电袭击
Hey, hey, LBJ!
嘿，嘿, LBJ!（LBJ=约翰逊总统）
How many kids  did you kill today?!
你今天杀了多少个孩子?!
Hey,hey,LBJ!
嘿，嘿, LBJ!
How many kids  did you kill today?!
你今天杀了多少个孩子?!
...the ancient imperial city.
...古老的皇城.
It is to Vietnamese  what old Boston is to Americans,
它对越南人的意义就相当于  波士顿对于美国人的意义
where many of its country's  leaders are born or educated.
国家的许多领导者出生于那里  或者在那里接受教育
I wish they'd shut up.
我希望他们能闭嘴.
The first sniper shots ricochet  around the thick walls of the building,
狙击枪的子弹穿过了这所建筑厚厚的墙壁
taking the first casualties  of the first squad.
小组有一名士兵死亡
The snipers may be  only two or three,
可能一共有2名或者3名阻击手
invisible to the buildings  beyond the wall.
躲在墙壁后的某个地方.
But there is also a machine gun  down the street to the left.
在街道左面还有一架重机枪.
Dr. King, you might want to  lie down with that fever.
金博士，也许你也想发烧躺个几天吧
President Johnson is making  a tragic error in Vietnam.
约翰逊总统在越南犯了一个悲剧性的错误
Move over, big yellow.
挪开点儿, 大PP.
Why shouldn't we fight in Vietnam?
为什么我们不去越南打仗?
The Vietcong don't call us  "niggers," for one.
最起码，越共不会叫我们黑鬼
Seriously, how many of  your parents support the war?
认真点说，你们的父母中有多少人会支持战争?
Well, my Lord.  Why do your parents support it?
我的上帝呀.  为什么你们的父母会支持战争呢?
We haven't spoken about it specifically,  I just know they do.
我们并没有很明确地谈过  但是我知道他们会支持的
Well, what do your daddy do?
你爸爸是做什么的?
He's a butler.
他是一名男仆
The black domestic play an  important role in our history.
黑人佣人在我们的历史中扮演着非常重要的角色
I didn't tell you that  to make fun of me.
我跟你说那个，并不是让你取笑我的.
Young brother, the black  domestic defy racial stereotypes
兄弟，黑人佣人一直在以他们辛勤工作的态度
by being hardworking and trustworthy.
和可以信赖的忠诚  在对抗种族偏见
He slowly  tears down racial hatred
他在以他的强烈的职业道德和  高贵的品格
with his example of a strong work ethic  and dignified character.
逐渐地驳斥和瓦解着所谓的种族仇恨
Now, while we perceive the butler  or the maid to be subservient,
现在，我们在批评那些男仆和女仆们  屈从的态度
in many ways, they are subversive,  without even knowing it.
在许多方面，他们的确是很顺从  但那是一种无意识的顺从
- Come in, Cecil.  - Afternoon, Mr. Warner.
- 请进，塞西尔.  - 下午好，沃纳先生.
Thank you for seeing me.
谢谢您能见我.
Since the colored...
因为有色...
...the black staff
...因为黑人员工
does just as much work  as the white staff,
所做的工作和白人员工所做同样多,
I believe that our salaries  should reflect our service, sir.
我相信我们的薪水应该也能  体现在我们的服务上面，先生
"Black" staff?
黑人员工?
I also feel  that we should have...
而且我也觉得我们应该能有...
...opportunities of advancement.
...升职的机会.
No black houseman
从来没有任何一名黑人男仆
has ever been promoted  to the engineer's office.
被提拔为技术人员.
You're very well liked here, Cecil.
塞西尔，看起来你非常喜欢这里.
But if you're unhappy  with your salary or position,
但如果你对你的薪水和职位不满意
then I suggest you seek  employment elsewhere.
那我建议你去其他地方找工作吧
- With all due respect...  - Don't let that Martin Luther King shit
- 恕我冒昧...  - 别让那个马丁路德金的狗屁言论
fill your britches out.  Just remember where I found you.
搞得你头脑发热.  别忘记了我是从哪儿找到你的
Yes, sir.
是的，先生.
Excuse me.
抱歉.
Dr. Martin Luther King,  the apostle of non-violence
马丁.路德.金博士,  和平与非暴力的民权运动的倡导者
in the civil rights movement has been  shot to death in Memphis, Tennessee.
在田纳西州孟菲斯市遭遇枪击身亡
Police have issued  an All Points Bulletin
警方已经发布了全面通缉凶犯的通告
for a well-dressed, young white  man seen running from the scene.
目击者声称有一名衣着考究的年轻白人男子  匆匆离开案发现场
Officers also reportedly  chased and fired on
据报道，警官曾经追捕一辆  安装有无线电装备的车辆
a radio-equipped car  containing two white men.
车内载有两名白人男子  并且警方曾向该车辆开火.
I didn't know if I was  gonna get home alive.
我不知道我是否能活着回到家.
It was the first time I felt like  I didn't belong in my own neighborhood.
这是我头一次觉得  我并不属于我居住的那个社区.
The whole world was changing,
整个世界都变了
and I didn't know where I fit in.
我也不知道适合我的地方在哪里
Dr. King has been a buffer  the last two years,
过去的两年里，马丁路德金博士的身份一直是一名男仆
between the black community  and the white community.
他一直游走于白人社区和黑人社区之间
The white people do not know it,
白人并不知道他是谁
but the white people's  best friend is dead.
但是白人最好的朋友死了
The black people's leader, our Moses,
黑人的领路人，我们的摩西
the once in a four-  or five-hundred year leader,
几百年来我们唯一的领路人,
has been taken from us  by hatred and bitterness.
也因为痛苦和憎恨  离开了我们
Even as I stand at this hour,
即使是此时此刻，我站在这里
I cannot even allow hate  to enter my heart at this time,
我都无法允许仇恨涌进我的心中
for it was sickness,  not meanness, that killed him.
因为仇恨是一种病态的心理.
Ma... my room's pink.
妈妈... 我的房间是粉色的.
Make sure you get some more  of my sweet potatoes, Carol.
你得多吃点我做的白薯，卡萝尔.
I use orange juice  when I make 'em,
我在里边加了橙汁,
that's what make 'em so... tart.
那会让它们吃起来有股酸酸的味道.
How long y'all been dating?
你们俩在一起多久了?
- Five years.  - We're just friends.
- 5年了.  - 我们俩只是朋友而已.
Is, uh,  all the rest of the students
噢，其余的学生们
are they getting involved  in politics, too?
他们也都参与政治活动吗?
There's been a division.  Kind of a split, Ma.
我们都有各自的分工  我们现在有一点点分裂,妈妈
A few of them,  like John Lewis, they're still...
他们中的几个，比如约翰.路易斯  他们还在...
- I love John Lewis.  - How you know who John Lewis is?
- 我喜欢约翰.路易斯.  - 你怎么知道约翰.路易斯是谁?
'Cause, honey,  I read Jet magazine.
因为，亲爱的，我有读JET杂志
I'm not just sitting up there  sewing for you all day.
我又不是整天坐在这里  就知道给你缝缝补补
Ooh.
噢.
I'm sick and tired of getting  thrown in jail.
我已经厌倦了待在监狱里的日子.
Yeah, well, that makes  two of us, don't it?
嗯，我也一样
Dr. King's philosophy ultimately  got him murdered.
金博士的人生观最终  导致了他被谋杀
It worked when we started,
当我们刚刚开始起步的时候  他的那一套很有用
but... now it's time to take  the next step, which is politics.
但是... 现在已经是时候进行下一步行动了  这就是政治
So y'all going  to the White House now?
所以，你们都要去白宫?
Daddy, Louis going  to the White House.
爸爸，路易斯要去白宫
You know they ain't gonna  let you in there
你知道他们不会让你进去那里的
with them nipples out.
尤其是你还穿着那种袒胸露乳的衣服
Maybe one, but not both of 'em.
也许你们中的一个人可以进去  但是肯定不会让你们两个都进不去
Shut up. Nah, we're...  we're more grass roots.
闭嘴. 我们...  我们大部分都是草根平民.
One-on-one with the community.
我们可以直接跟所有成员联络.
Although we have started  our own political party.
虽然我们已经成立了我们自己的政党
What's your party?
你的政党是什么?
You like to party?
你喜欢派对?（Party 双关语）
I like to party.  What's your party called?
我喜欢派对  你的派对叫什么?
The Black Panther Party.
黑豹党.（一个左翼黑人民权组织）.
What kind of name is that?  What's that stand for?
那是什么名字啊?  那表示什么意义?
We... provide free breakfast  for children,
我们... 为孩子们提供免费的早餐
free medical clinics, free clothing,  self-defense classes.
免费的医疗诊所, 免费的衣物,  我们还提供自我防御课程.
And why y'all need self-defense?
为什么你们需要自我防御?
We ain't gettin' beat no more.
我们不会再被他们打败了
Me and your daddy saw a  wonderful movie the other night.
前几天我和你爸爸  看了一个很棒的电影.
Reminded me so much of you.
那电影让我想起很多有关你的事
Oh, yeah?
是吗?
What was the name  of that movie, honey?
亲爱的，那电影叫什么名字来着?
In the Heat of the Night.
炎热的夜晚  （第40届奥斯卡金像奖最佳影片）
In the Heat... of the Night,  with Sidney Poitier.
炎热的... 夜晚,  是西德尼·波蒂埃演的吧.
Lord, Sidney Poitier.  I love Sidney Poitier.
天哪，是西德尼·波蒂埃.  我喜欢西德尼·波蒂埃.
Sidney Poitier's a white man's fantasy  of what he wants us to be.
西德尼·波蒂埃就是白人们的理想人物  他们希望我们都变成西德尼·波蒂埃那样
But his movies have him  fighting for equal rights.
但是在他的电影中，他也在为了平等权在奋斗
Only in a way that's acceptable  to the white status quo.
但那种平等只是建立在接受  目前这种以白人主导一切的现状的前提之上
- Ah.  - The brother can't act.
- 噢.  - 可那是行不通的.
What are you talking about?
你说什么呢?
He just won the Academy Award.
他刚刚赢得了奥斯卡金像奖.
He's breaking down barriers  for all of us.
他为我们所有人打开了一道屏障
By being white.  By acting white.
那只是以白人的方式而已
Sidney Poitier is nothing but  a rich Uncle Tom.
西德尼·波蒂埃只是一个有钱的汤姆叔叔而已  除此之外他什么都不是
Look at you.
看看你自己.
All puffed up.
一幅自负的、愤愤不平的样子
With your hat on your head.
还戴着那么一顶奇形怪状的帽子.
Coming in here,  saying whatever you want.
回到这里,  满嘴跑火车.
Girlfriend belching at the table.
女朋友还在饭桌上直打嗝
You don't even feel  you gotta go to school,
即使是拿着我给你的钱
even though I gave you the money.
你都没觉得你应该回去上学
You need to go.
你该走了
Yeah, Louis.  I need you to get out of my house.
是的，路易斯  请你离开我的房间
- What?  - Get the hell out of my house!
- 你说什么?  - 你给我滚出我的房间!
- What are you doing?  - Get on out!
- 你在做什么?  - 滚出去!
- He's gotta go!  - No, Cecil, no!
- 他必须得离开!  - 不，塞西尔，不要!
- I can't take this no more!  - We ain't seen this boy!
- 我再也无法忍受这一切了!  - 我们不会再见到他了!
We ain't seen this boy!
我们不会再见到他了!
I'm gonna snatch the life  out of you, boy!
以后你的生活跟我无关
- Now, everybody just sit down.  - I'm sorry, Mr. Butler,
- 现在，大家都坐下  - 我很抱歉，男仆先生
I didn't mean to make  fun of your hero.
我并不是故意要取笑你的英雄.
Everything you are and  everything you have is...
你的生命，以及你所拥有的一切...
...'cause of that butler.
...都是那个男仆给你的.
Now you take that trifling  low-class bitch...
现在，带着你那位轻浮的品质低劣的婊子...
...and get out of this house.
...滚出这所房子.
I like Sidney Poitier, Daddy.
爸爸，我喜欢西德尼·波蒂埃.
What's that movie he did?  Look Who's Coming to Dinner?
他演的那部电影叫什么来着?  看看谁来吃晚饭了?
Everything ain't a joke.
别开玩笑了.
- Carol came to dinner.  - Hush, Charlie.
- 卡萝尔来吃晚餐了.  - 嘘，查理.
Police took Louis the next day.
第二天，警察带走了路易斯.
Y'all gonna make me late for work.
你们要害我迟到了.
Unc, I'm sorry.
嗯，对不起
Who else I'm supposed to call  to bail him out?
我还能找谁来保释他出去呢?
What they got him in for this time?  Sit up!
这次他们又是为了什么把他抓进来的?  坐起来!
Louis said they  stopped him just because.
路易斯说他们抓他是因为
Just because.
因为.
He said he wasn't going  to get beat no more, so...
他说他不会再被打败了，所以...
...he got out the car  and he hit 'em back.
...他下了车，并且回击了他们
What about that little gal of his?
那他的那位小妞呢?
They put her in the hospital.
他们送她去了医院
The hospital.
医院
Charlie.
查理.
This shit's gotta stop, man.
这些破事必须得停止了.
I'm late for work.
我上班要迟到了
You tell Louis I'm not his mama.
你转告路易斯，我不是他妈.
I want my money back.
而且我希望拿回我的钱
You all right?
你没事吧?
Yeah, I'm all right.
嗯，我没事.
Thanks, Uncle Carter.
谢谢, 卡特叔叔
You need to take all this Black  Panther shit somewhere else.
你必须得带着你的那些  狗屁黑豹党的东东去其他地方
Now, I'm not them.  I want my money back, hear me?
现在，我要你把我的钱还给我，你听到了吗?
- Yes, sir.  - Every dime.
- 是的，先生  - 每一分钱.
- Yes, sir.  - Hey, Unc... don't tell Daddy.
- 是的，先生.  - 喂，叔叔，别告诉我爸爸.
How you avoid all that sex  in prison?
在监狱里你是如何避开那些性行为的?
Do they teach you that  with the Panthers?
那个什么黑豹党有没有教你那些事?
They teach you how to... to sit...
他们教你如何坐......
- She been drinking again?  - No. She's sober.
- 她又开始喝酒了吗?  - 没有，她很清醒.
She ain't doing nothing but sewing  and feeding them damn fishes.
她一天到晚什么都不干，除了做缝纫工作  和喂养她的那些鱼
Feed them more than she feed me.
喂给它们的比喂给我的还多.
You excited about  going back to Howard?
回去霍华德是不是让你很兴奋?
Excited about not going back.
我很兴奋因为我不用再回去那里了.
- What?  - Yeah.
- 什么?  - 是的.
I'm going to Vietnam.
我要去越南啦.
Charlie, don't do this.  Don't do this.
查理，不要那么做  不要那么做.
- This country treats us like dogs!  - And do what? Don't do this?
- 这个国家对待我们就像是狗一样!  - 那么做什么，做这事儿?
You fight your country.
你在为你的国家而战
I want to fight for my country.
而我想要为我的国家而战.
- I won't go to your funeral.  - Good.
- 我不会去参加你的葬礼.  - 很好.
'Cause I don't want you there  with all of that...
因为我也不想让你穿着那些亮晶晶的...
...black leather and latex,
...奇装异服出现在我的葬礼上
shining and taking away the attention  off of my pretty face in my casket.
吸引走那些原本应该停留在  我的英俊的脸蛋儿的注意力
What do they call you now, Louise?
他们现在怎么称呼你, 路易斯?
- Shut up.  - Louise Gaines.
- 闭嘴.  - 路易斯 盖恩斯.
Charlie, shut up.
查理，闭嘴.
I want to know every goddamn  domestic policy decision right now,
我需要马上知道每一项该死的国内政策,
and I want it on the table right now.
我要让他们立刻出现在我的书桌上.
- OK.  - OK.
- 好的.  - 好的
Did you get  the memos we sent last week?
你收到上周我们寄给你的备忘录了吗?
John and I strongly agree  that the time calls for...
约翰和我强烈赞同...
A goddamn fly,  a goddamn fly in here.
一只该死的苍蝇,  这里有一只该死的苍蝇.
- Jesus Christ.  - John and I both think
- 天哪.  - 约翰和我都认为
that the time calls for  a period of benign neglect.
现在需要采取善意忽视的策略.
- Benign neglect.  - Yes.
- 善意忽视?  - 是的.
I like that. I like that.
我喜欢那个.我喜欢那个.
You know, the pigs in the  media describe us as terrorists.
你知道, 媒体的那些猪们  都把我们描述成恐怖分子了
A terrorist is one who  terrorizes and frightens others.
恐怖份子是指那些恐吓和威胁他人的人
We the ones getting terrorized.
我们才是被恐吓的人.
How can we exist in, in peace,
当我们在大街上在商店里  都不敢讲话的时候
when we scared to walk  down the street to the store?
我们如何才能和平共处呢
All right, there's this whole black  power movement going on, right?
好，现在的黑人权利运动正在进行，对吗?
- Right.  - What if we, um...
- 对.  - 假如我们...
What if Nixon promotes black power
假如尼克松决定推动和提升黑人的权利
to mean "black businesses"  and we find ways to support
我是说，支持黑人企业家  只要我们找到合适的支持他们的方式
black entrepreneurs, pass the buck  on desegregation to the courts.
而把废除种族歧视的责任推卸给法院
Push black enterprise
那将可以使我们赢得20%的选票
to win the 2O percent  of the votes it could swing our way.
而且会打破目前这种僵持的局面
- Excellent, sir.  - Absolutely.
- 这招太高了，先生.  - 绝对的.
You don't know if your ceiling gonna  cave in 'cause your slum lord
你永远都不知道你的顶棚什么时候会塌  因为你的平民窟老板...
too busy running around  collecting rent checks.
正在忙着四处收取他的房租支票呢
But he won't fix your roof.
他不会帮你修理你的屋顶
It's time we take a stand  against these injustices
现在是时候该表明立场和采取行动
that have plagued our community.
来对抗这些已困扰我们很久了的不公.
They take one of ours,  we taking two of theirs.
他们抓走我们中的一个人  那我们就要抓走他们中的两个人.
- That's right.  - It's been time.
- 对.  - 现在是时候了.
We just need to make sure  that Nixon black power
我们只需要确定  所谓的尼克松黑人权利
doesn't equate Nixon  with the Black Panthers.
并不等于尼克松 + 黑豹党
Have you lost your mind, man?  Did you read Hoover's last memo on that?
你疯了吗?  你没有读过胡佛的上一个备忘录?
- That's my point.  - Goddamn terrifying.
- 那就是我说的重点.  - 太可怕了.
No, no, no. I gave him the green light  to gut those sons of bitches.
不不不. 我已经给他开了一路绿灯  让他去找出那些婊子养的黑豹党
- Good.  - Good. Absolutely.
- 很好.  - 绝对的.
No, round 'em all up and  throw 'em down an elevator shaft.
要把他们都弄在一起  然后把它们都丢进升降机井.
I don't proclaim to know everything.  But I promise you...
我不会说我无所不知.  但是我向你们保证..
...they'll always beware  of the nigger with a gun.
...他们总是很惧怕拿着枪的黑鬼
Will there be anything else,  Mr. President?
还有其他事吗, 总统先生?
How many kids we got coming  to the breakfast tomorrow morning?
明天早晨我们要带多少孩子去餐馆?
Got about 25 to 3O coming.
大概25至30个吧.
Twenty-five to 3O kids  will be able to go to school
这25至30个孩子本来可以去学校
and focus on their lessons.
专心上课.
'Cause they don't want us  to be able to feed our kids.
但因为他们不想让我们有能力养活我们的孩子
They don't want us  to be able to protect ourselves.
因为他们不想让我们有能力保护我们自己
What are we doing here?
我们在这里做什么?
Thought this was going to be  our community service.
我以为我们是在做我们的社区服务
This is community service.
这就是社区服务.
"Someone kills one of ours,  we kill two of theirs?"
"有人杀了我们中的一个,  我们要杀了他们中的两个?"
Community protection.
这是社区保护.
Are you ready to kill somebody, Carol?
你准备好去杀人了吗, 卡萝尔?
'Cause I ain't.
因为我还没有准备好
I am.
我准备好了
Did you ever love me, baby?
你有没有爱过我，宝贝?
Today, a day after police  shot it outwith the Black Panthers,
今天， 在警察和黑豹党交火后的第二天
killing two of them,  they raided the apartment...
警察又击毙了两名黑豹党成员  他们包围了黑豹党成员的公寓...
...the shooting of 26  Panthers in the past year,
...过去一年里，警方一共击毙了26名黑豹党成员
may represent a national campaign  by police to wipe out the Panthers...
这可能也表示警方将会
...the criminal reaction  of the occupants in shooting
在全国范围对黑豹党进行彻底地剿灭
at announced police officers,
警方也宣布了......
emphasizes the extreme viciousness  of the Black Panther Party.
并且强调指出黑豹党....
"Party ls a Groovy Thing"]
- Hey, baby-  - Hey.
- 嗨，宝贝  - 嗨.
- Happy birthday.  - Happy birthday to me, huh?
- 生日快乐.  - 祝我生日快乐呀?
Happy birthday to you.
祝你生日快乐.
Right now, this is the present  I want, right here.
此时此刻, 我想要的生日礼物就在这里
Well, you want it right here?
噢，你现在就想要吗?
Mm-mm, you know right...
嗯，你知道的...
- Right here?  - Kids up... Kids down...?
- 就在这里?  - 孩子在楼上还是在楼下...?
Ain't no kids in the house no more.
这所房子里再也有没有孩子了
Hey, I made you a birthday cake.
我给你做了一只生日蛋糕.
I got all the cake  I want right here.
我想吃的蛋糕就在这里啦.
No, you crazy.
不要啦，你个疯子.
I got some champagne  cooling in the icebox.
我准备了一些香槟  正在冷冻室冰镇着呢
And some ice cream, too.  Get some ice cream.
还有一些冰淇淋  要吃点吗
You gonna be drinking with me?
你要跟我一起喝吗?
You know I don't drink.
你知道我不喝酒的.
I don't drink.
我不喝酒
Just playing with you.
我是在逗你玩啦
I just want to see you move  a little bit. Go ahead.
我想看你扭几下，快点儿啦.
' 9h, my God!
噢，天哪!
We get any mail  from Charlie today?
今天有没有收到查理的来信?
No.
没有
- No?  - Haven't heard from Charlie.
- 没有?  - 查理一直没有音讯.
I know. I got an idea.
我知道. 我有个主意.
I think we should go  to Shantay's tonight.
我觉得今晚我们应该去Shantay跳舞
Oh, no.  No, I'm too old for disco.
噢，不. 我都这把年纪了  已经不适合去跳迪斯科了
We not old. Come on. We ain't old.
我们还不老啦，走吧.  我们还没那么老.
I just don't feel like  doing no disco.
我只是不想去跳迪斯科
Our boys are gone.  It's just you and me.
我们的儿子们走来  现在只剩下你和我
You and me, we are free.  I forgot this. I forgot this.
你和我，我们俩现在自由了  噢，我都忘记这个东东了
Now, look at us.  Little happy birthday present.
现在，看着这个小小的生日礼物
I want you to go put it on, upstairs.
我想让你上楼去换上它
- Put it on?  - Yeah. Go put it on.
- 穿上?  - 对，去穿上.
- All right.  - Make it snappy.
- 好吧.  - 迅速点.
Bring down my sewing kit,  'cause I need to do some alterations.
顺便把我的针线包拿下来  可能我得帮你改一改
Make it snappy!
迅速点!
Hello.
你好.
Hi. Where are you?
嗨，你在哪儿?
Where?
哪里?
You should call me back,  because this is not a good time.
你应该回头再打给我  因为现在这个时间不太合适
- He's home again.  - It fit!
- 他在家.  - 很合适呀!
- We gonna go on out tonight.  - Where?
- 今晚我们要出去咯.  - 哪儿?
- He's home and...  - Boy, you good, aren't you?
- 他在家，而且...  - 你还好吧?
- You all right?  - Who that?
- 你没事吧?  - 那是谁?
Call me back.
回头打给我.
- OK?  - Oh, it's Louis.
- 好吗?  - 噢，是路易斯呀.
He asking for some money?
他又打电话来要钱?
Hey, Louis.
嗨，路易斯
I didn't expect to hear  from you on my birthday.
我过生日的时候可没指望你打电话来
You should feel  ashamed of yourself.
你应该为自己感到羞耻.
You're a grown-ass man calling  your mama, asking for money.
你现在是个成年人了  居然还打电话跟你妈妈要钱
And guess what?  It's the butler's money.
你猜猜怎么着?  这可都是男仆先生的钱.
It's Uncle Tom's money.
是汤姆叔叔的钱
And he ain't giving  none out today.
而且，今天他一个子儿都不会给你的
Bye.
拜
I got it.
我明白了
You got the wrong house.
你找错地方了.
It's the wrong house.
你好错地方了.
翻译： @ 塔拉Tala
Vietnam took my boy,
越南带走了我的儿子
and I didn't understand why we  were there in the first place.
打一开始我就不明白为什么我们要去那里
Your father still alive, Cecil?
你爸爸还活着吗 ,塞西尔 ?
No, sir.
没有，先生
My father died when I was a child.
我还是孩子的时候他就死了
Is there anything else that you  would like, Mr. President?
你还想要点什么吗，总统先生?
Yeah. Come sit.
对，过来坐下.
Sit down, you know?
请坐, 你知道吗?
There's been a lot of talk  of me resigning and...
最近一段时间，有关让我辞职下台...
...things of that nature,  but I just want you to know
...等等这类说法比比皆是  但是我只想让你知道
it's never gonna happen.
那是绝对不会发生的.
I'm gonna come out of this thing  stronger than ever.
经过这事儿，会让我变得前所未有的强大
Is there anything else  that you would like...
你还想要点儿什么吗...
...Mr. President?
...总统先生?
Louis is here, looking for you.
路易斯在这里, 他在找你.
- Got everybody all worried.  - Well, I finished school.
- 大家都很担心你.  - 我读完大学了.
I got my master's  in political science.
我拿到了社会学的硕士学位
Hey! That's what I'm talking about.
哇噢，我就说嘛
Get that education.
要好好读书.
There he is!  Well, I'm gonna let you all to it.
他来了!  好吧，你们俩好好聊吧.
Ain't no need for that, Carter.
卡特，你不需要离开.
- Hey, Dad.  - Get out of here, Louis.
- 嗨，爸爸  - 离开这里，路易斯.
- Dad...  - I said leave.
- 爸爸...  - 我说了，你走吧.
Keep doing what you doing.
继续做好你在做的事
Thank you, Uncle Carter.
谢谢你，卡特叔叔.
Why you do that? Huh?  That was wrong.
为什么你要那么做? 啊?  那是不对的.
That boy's hurting, too. He's just  trying to get his act together.
那个孩子也一样受到了伤害  他只是在设法振作起来.
He should be hurting, Carter.
他应该受到伤害,卡特.
Boy didn't even go  to his own brother's funeral.
他甚至都没有去参加他弟弟的葬礼.
He's full of shit is what he is.  He ain't doing nothing right.
他就是狗屎一坨  他就没做对过任何事.
He just got his master's!  What more you want him to do?
他刚刚拿到了他的硕士学位  你还想让他怎么样?
Every gray hair I have  is 'cause of that boy.
我的每一个白头发都是为他操心操的
The years started to drift by,
一年又一年，时间缓慢地在流逝,
but the pain in my heart  never went away.
但是深植于我内心深处的痛苦却从未消失
"You and I Ain't Nothin' No More"]
Through it all,  Louis and I never spoke.
经过了那么多事以后  我和路易斯再也没有讲过话
As we are a nation under God,  so I am sworn...
因为我们是上帝庇佑下的一个国家,  所以，我发过誓...
Half of our  oil is now imported...
现在，我们有一半石油都依靠进口...
It is a crisis that strikes  at the very hear':
这对每一个人
and soul and spirit  of our national will.
以及我们的国家的精神和灵魂都是一次打击
- I feel one coming now.  - Not to worry.
- 有人来了.  - 别担心.
Two of you,  stay home until you feel better.
你们俩个,  待在家里直到你们感觉好一点再来
OK, Barn, I'll stay.  But I ain't never gonna feel no better.
好的， 巴纳，我会带在家里  但是那也无法让我感觉更好
In our district alone,  we have nine percent unemployment.
在我们这个街区  我们有百分之九的人都失业在家.
In the country at large, 14 percent  are living below the poverty line.
在这个广袤的国家,  还有14%的人生活在贫困线以下
Sixty percent of those  are either black or Hispanic.
而在那些人之中  60%的人不是黑人就是拉丁裔
Now, if I'm voted to Congress,  reducing those figures is gonna be
现在，我首要的目标  就是致力于推动国会投票
one of my primary objectives.
来改善这种情况  降低那些惊人的数据
Yeah?
你好?
Oh, hey.
噢，嗨.
Thanks for getting back to me.
谢谢你回电话给我.
How much did he lose by?
他损失了多少?
Really?
真的吗?
All right, then.
那好吧.
I appreciate it.
我很感激
No, he didn't win.
没有，他没有赢.
I think you should call him.
我想你应该打电话给他
Right after Charlie passed,
查理过世之后,
Louis came over  and paid me a visit.
路易斯过来看过我一次
Hmm.
嗯.
He found me on the kitchen floor.
他发现我躺在厨房的地板上.
I had passed out.
我当时神志不清.
Drunk.
我喝多了
I'd gone to the bathroom  all over myself.
我在卫生间吐得自己全身都是.
He's the one that cleaned me up.
是他帮我清理干净那些污物.
And then he told me  I was the best mother
然后他告诉我说  我是世界上最好的...
anybody could ever want.
每个人都向往的妈妈
I think, about now...
我想, 现在...
...he'd want to hear from his daddy.
...他一定很想听到他爸爸的声音.
I think you ought to call him.
我想你应该打电话给他.
Mm-hm.
嗯
Cecil?
塞西尔?
Yes, sir, Mr. President.
是的，总统先生.
You stay there, I'm coming to you.
你待在那里，我过去找你.
I... have a...
我... 有一个...
...secret mission for you.
...秘密任务要交给你.
Yes, sir.
好的，先生.
I like to send people  money when they write me
我很想寄一些钱给那些写信给我...
about their financial problems,
面临财政问题的人们
but my staff has been  trying to get me to stop.
但是我的职员一直在试着阻止我这么做.
You think you could  help me to keep this going?
你可以帮助我继续做这件事吗?
Absolutely, Mr. President.
没问题，总统先生.
Well, I appreciate  your help with this.
我很感激你能这么做.
And, please, don't tell Nancy.
还有，请不要告诉南茜
Of course not.
我不会的.
- Morning, Cecil.  - Morning, Mr. Warner.
- 早上好，塞西尔.  - 早上好，沃纳先生
May I sit down?
我可以坐下吗?
I've been here  for over 2O years now.
到现在为止  我在这里工作已经超过20年了.
For all that time,  the black help
过去的这些年  黑人员工所拿到的薪水
has been paid a smaller salary  than the white help.
一直比白人员工的薪水低很多
And I just don't think  that's right, Mr. Warner.
我就只觉得这是不对的，沃纳先生.
There are black housemen  who should be engineers by now.
现在，这里有很多黑人男仆  都应该成为工程师
They should've been promoted  years ago.
其实许多年前他们就应该升职了.
You think so?
你这么认为吗?
I'm gonna have to be paid  the same as the white help,
我也应该拿到和白人员工同等的薪水
or I'm gonna have to move on.
不然我就只好离开了.
I guess you'll be moving on then.
那我猜你最好还是走人吧.
I told the president  that you'd say that.
我会把你的意思转达给总统先生.
He told me to tell you  to take this up with him, personally.
他让我转告你，他会亲自着手处理这事儿的
Excuse me.
我先走了
I'm not comfortable  with all the foreign policy hawks
吉姆，我不喜欢那些提倡强硬的外交政策...
surrounding Ronnie, Jim.
的鹰派人物整天围着罗尼转
We need more moderates on his staff.  And a summit with the Russians.
我们需要更多的温和派成员在他身边  还有，这次与俄国人的峰会.
Ronnie has to meet  with them face to face
如果我们打算撬动这座冰山
if we're ever  going to thaw this ice.
罗尼就必须要跟他们亲自会面
- Cecil.  - Yes, Mrs. Reagan?
- 塞西尔.  - 是，里根夫人?
We will talk, Jim. Yes.
我们回头再谈，吉姆.
Yes, ma'am?
夫人?
You're very popular around here.
你在这里非常受欢迎呀.
Everyone says you're the man  that got them raises and promotions.
所有的人都说是你让他们  得到了升职和加薪的机会
- I had no idea.  - I wish I could take credit for that.
- 我居然都对此全然不知.  - 我希望我能接受这份功劳.
I'd like to invite you  to the State Dinner next week.
我想邀请你参加下周举行的国宴
- I'm gonna be there, Mrs. Reagan.  - No.
- 我会在那里的，里根先生.  - 不
Not as a... Not as a butler, Cecil.  I'm inviting you as a guest.
不是... 不是作为男仆，塞西尔.  我是邀请你作为宾客出席国宴.
But the president prefers  for me to serve him personally.
但是总统先生会更希望我亲自为他服务
Don't you worry about, Ronnie.  I'll take care of that.
你别担心那个，至于罗尼  我会照顾他的
So we'll see you next week.  You and your wife.
那么我们下周见  请带上你的夫人.
My Wife?
我夫人?
It's... It's Gloria, yes?
她... 她叫格罗瑞亚, 对吗?
- Yes, ma'am.  - Yes.
- 对，夫人.  - 嗯
Hmm.
嗯
Here's the Entrance Hall.
这里是门厅.
Beautiful.
真漂亮.
Can I get you a glass  of champagne, Mr. Gaines?
我可以帮你拿杯香槟吗, 盖恩斯先生?
- Shut up.  - Right.
- 闭嘴吧你  - 好的.
Ladies and gentlemen,
女士们先生们,
the President and First Lady  of the United States.
美国总统和第一夫人.
It was different sitting  at the table instead of serving it.
站在这个桌子旁服务  和坐在这里的感觉是那么地不同
Real different.
非常不同.
I could see the two faces  the butlers wore to survive.
我可以看到那些男仆们在服务时的  那张与平时完全的痛的脸孔
And I knew I'd lived my life  with those same two faces.
我知道在我的一生中，  我也始终以两张面孔示人
Gloria looked so happy,  but I didn't feel the same way.
格罗瑞亚看起来很开心  但是我并不觉得.
I guess I wished we were there  for real instead of for show.
我猜我所希望的是，我们能真的坐在那里  而不是为了作秀
I think that's bon appetit, everybody.
我猜大家都胃口都很好
You black mother...
你娘的...
I want to make myself clear  on this issue.
我想就这个问题表明我自己的态度
If Congress passes sanctions  against South Africa,
如果国会要让对南非的制裁决议通过
I will be forced to  veto those sanctions.
我将不得不否决这些制裁决议.
Well, Mr. President, we feel  that that would be a major mistake.
总统先生，我们觉得那会是一个绝对的错误
The brutal repression  of South African black citizens
南非对黑人平民残酷镇压的行为
makes this no longer  a foreign policy issue,
已经使得这一问题  不再单纯停留在外交政策的层面
but a United States racial issue.
而是牵扯到美国对于种族问题的态度
We're senators  from your own party.
我们是属于你自己的党派的参议员.
That's why we feel so comfortable  in letting you know
这也是为什么我们很想让你知道
that South Africa  is a human rights disaster.
南非现在存在很严重的人权问题
Black people are  being beaten, tortured,
黑人常年遭受欺压和折磨
gunned down  in the middle of the street.
甚至在大街上都会遭到枪击
Americans see all this on TV,  they're horrified by apartheid.
美国人可以从电视上看到这一切,  种族隔离让他们感到震惊
I've made my decision.
我已经做出决定了
Mr. President, your reputation  as a world leader is at stake.
总统先生，你作为世界领导者的声望  已经受到了影响
United States of America needs to be
就种族问题而言...
on the right side of history  on the race issue.
美国需要站在历史正确的一面
I say again.
我再说一遍.
If Congress passes this bill,
如果国会会通过这个法案,
I Will veto it.
我会提出否定
Peﬂod.
句号.
What? You reading now?
什么? 你又在读书?
Get up and do the dishes  'fore I shoot your little ass.
快点起来，在我射飞你的小脑袋之前  快点把这些盘子都洗干净.
Nothing seemed right to me  after that State Dinner.
那次晚宴之后  好像我周围的任何事看起来都不对劲了
Got all confused.
我总是感到很困惑.
They had started writing books
他们开始把那些有关路易斯
about everything Louis  and his friends had done.
和他的朋友们所做的事情  写成文章，写成书
Louis was never a criminal.
路易斯不再是一名罪犯.
He was a hero,
他变成了一名英雄,
fighting to save  the soul of our country.
变成了一名为了拯救我们国家的灵魂的斗士
- Would you like a cookie?  - Thank you, sir.
- 你要来电而饼干吗?  - 谢谢你，先生.
- Cookies.  - Thank you.
- 饼干.  - 谢谢你.
Cookie?
饼干?
- Thank you.  - Thank you.
- 谢谢你  - 谢谢你
Thank you.
谢谢你
Cookie?
饼干?
I had always loved sewing.  But just felt different now.
我一直很喜欢我的工作.  但是现在却觉得有点儿不同
I didn't know that an old man  could feel so lost.
我不知道是不是每一个老人  都会有失落和无助的感觉
That's how I felt.
可是. 我是那么地失落
那么地无助
Americans always turned
美国人对于我们对自己人所犯下的错误
a blind eye to what we'd done  to our own.
总是采取视而不见的态度
We look out to the world and judge.
却很喜欢对其他国家的事指手画脚
We hear about  the concentration camps,
我们听说了那些集中营的故事,
but these camps went on  for 200 years
但是就在美国，就在我们自己的土地上
right here in America.
这样的营地却已经存在了200年之久
Buried my daddy right over there.
我的爸爸就埋葬在那变边
My mama would've been  right proud of me,
我妈妈一定会以我为荣,
being with a man like you's.
因为我嫁了一个像你这么好的男人
Taking such good care of me  all of these years.
这么多年一直那么照顾我  那么疼爱我
I love you, Cecil Gaines.
我爱你，塞西尔 盖恩斯.
I love you more, Gloria.
我更爱你，格罗瑞亚
Are you sure about this?
你确定你要这么做吗?
Yes, sir.
是的
I just want to be the one  to tell you first, that's all.
我只是想第一个告诉你
But you're the best butler here.
但是你是这里最棒的男仆.
You're like family, Cecil.
对我来说，你就像家人一样，塞西尔
Been an honor serving you.
能服侍你是我的荣幸
Well, not just for me,  I'm sure I speak for all the presidents
不止是我，我可以代表所有的总统说
when I say that you've  served your country well.
你为你的国家提供了最好的服务
Thank you, Mr. President.
谢谢你，总统先生
Cecil?
塞西尔?
This whole civil rights issue...
有关所有的这些民权问题...
I sometimes fear I'm...
有时候我会害怕我...
on the wrong side of it,  that I'm...
站在了错误的一面, 嗯....我...
...just wrong.
...做错了
Sometimes I think I'm just  scared of what it really means.
有时候我觉得我很害怕  那些事情所蕴含的真正的意义
But I'm trying not to be  so scared anymore.
但是我会试着不要再害怕.
- Who do we want to free?!  - Mandela!
- 我们想让谁获得自由?!  - 曼德拉!
When do we want him free?
我们想让谁获得自由?!
- Now!  - Free Mandela!
- 立刻!  - 释放曼德拉!!
Twenty years ago, we marched  in this country for our rights.
20年前, 我们在这个国家为争取我们的权利而游行
Today, we march to free  the people of South Africa.
今天，我们游行是为了为南非的同胞争取自由
Yeah!
对!
Ronald Reagan has attacked or dismantled  every civil rights program
罗纳德.里根在  攻击和破坏我们的每一项
that has ever been put in place.
正在进行的民权计划
- Yeah!  - Right!
- 对!  - 对i!
Aiding the oppression of black South  Africans is absolutely consistent
他一直在以他的种族问题的政策来
with his policies on race issues.  Am I right?
协助压迫南非的黑人  我说的对吗?
- Am I right?  - Yes!
- 我说得对吗?  - 对!
Hold on, hold on.
等等，等一下
Excuse me. Steven?  Where's Steven?
斯蒂文，斯蒂文在哪儿?
- Free Mandela!  - Free Mandela, y'all!
- 释放曼德拉!  - 释放曼德拉!
Free Mandela!
释放曼德拉!
Free Mandela!  Free Mandela! Free Mandela!
释放曼德拉!  释放曼德拉!释放曼德拉!
Hi, Dad.
嗨，爸爸
Hi, Louis.
嗨，路易斯
What are you doing here?
你在这里做什么?
I came here to protest with you.
我来这里和你一起抗议.
You'll get arrested, Dad.  You'll lose your job.
你会被逮捕的，爸爸  你会丢了你的工作
I lost you.
我弄丢了你
I'm sorry.
对不起
I'm sorry, son.
对不起，儿子
Don't worry, Dad, we'll be  out of here in a few hours.
别担心，爸爸  几个小时后我们就会出去的
Who said I was worried?
谁说我会担心的?
After going to jail,  I thought I'd seen it all.
我离开监狱以后  我想我已经明白了一切
- You OK, Daddy?  - Yeah, no, no, no. I'm good.
- 你还好吗，爸爸?  - 嗯，不，不，我没事.
But I never imagined I'd see...
但是我从未想像过我会见到...
...a black man
...一个黑人
be a real contender for  the President of the United States.
会真的成为一名美国总统的竞选人
Here we go.
我们开始吧.
- It's that sweet corn.  - That corn look good.
- 这是甜玉米.  - 那个玉米看上去看不错.
Gloria and I would walk  to our polling place
每天晚上，格罗瑞亚和我都会  去我们的投票地点...
every night to see where  we'd be voting for Barack Obama.
我们就是在那里  为贝拉克·奥巴马投出了我们的选票
We'd just... stare at it, smile.
我们只是坐在那里, 看着，笑着.
- You done?  - Pretty much.
- 你吃完了吗?  - 差不多了.
Good. Time to go.
很好，我们该走了
You done pretty good there.
你在照片里看起来非常棒.
Thanks, honey.
谢谢，亲爱的.
How come Louis' wife  named that child...
为什么路易斯的妻子要给那个孩子取名叫...
- ...Shaquanda?  - Now, don't start that again.
- ... 史旷达?  - 现在可别再提这茬儿了.
I ain't starting it, I just don't know  what kind of name that is.
我又没提啦, 我只是不太明白  那名字究竟是个啥意思
I mean, really! Shaquanda?
我是说真的啦，史旷达?
I think she done that just to spite me.
我想她起那么名字可能就是为了气我
Ain't nobody  done nothing to spite you.
这里没有任何人会做任何事来气你啦.
Yes, she did.
嗯，她肯定是.
She a ugly little old girl, too.  That little pug nose.
她就是一个丑陋的小丫头  你瞧她那个扁扁的塌鼻子
- I hope she grow out of it.  - Now, you need to stop that.
- 我希望她的鼻子能再长大一点  - 别再唠叨那个啦.
- You know that ain't right.  - Don't you think
- 你知道你不应该那么想啦  - 难道你不觉得..
she look a little like  Louis around the mouth?
她的嘴巴有点儿像路易斯?
I think... she look just like you.
我觉得... 她看起来就跟你一样
- Like me?  - Yeah, so you need to...
- 像我?  - 对，所以你得...
...you need  to stop talking about her.
...你得停止再那么谈论她.
Let me look at her again,  then, real good.
让我再看看她，嗯，很好
Paughs]
She do look a little bit like me.  She a pretty little thing.
她看起来是有点儿像我.  她是个漂亮的小东西.
I guess I can put up  with the name Shaquanda.
我想我可以接受史旷达这个名字
I forgot where I put my Bible.
我忘了我把我的圣经放哪儿了.
- You know I need my Bible.  - Mm-hm.
- 你知道我需要我的圣经  - 嗯
- I think I left it in the bathroom.  - Why is Louis late?
- 我想我可能把它忘在洗手间了.  - 路易斯为什么迟到了?
Boy gets elected to Congress...
自从他当选议员之后...
...and he ain't been on time  getting us to church ever since.
...就很少能按时带我们去教堂了
- I can't believe you still... fussing.  - He gonna be late to his own funeral.
- 我都不敢相信你还在... 发牢骚.  - 我看他连去参加他自己的葬礼都会迟到
Are you still fussing  about Louis?
你还在为路易斯的事... 感到烦躁?
He said he's gonna be here for us.
他说了他会来这里接我们.
- Go ahead, call him.  - I ain't calling Louis.
- 去吧，打电话给他.  - 我才不会打电话给路易斯.
I'm gonna get my purse and...
我要拿上我的钱包，还有...
What'd you say? Isaiah?
你说什么? 以赛亚书?（圣经旧书）
I see you got... your mark here.
我看到你.. 在这里做了标记.
I'm gonna fall all over myself.
这玩意得把我绊倒在地
Baby, you need...  to move that to the other side.
宝贝，你得...  把它挪到另一边.
Baby?
宝贝?
Honey?
亲爱的?
You sleeping?
你睡着了?
Baby?
宝贝?
Are you all right?
你还好吗?
...states will be closing,
...投票站即将关闭,
and there are some big ones,  especially California,
那些都是胜算比较大的州,  特别是加利福尼亚
the largest state  in the United States,
加州美国最大的州,
with 55 electoral votes.
拥有55张选票.
Hawaii, that's where  Barack Obama was born.
在夏威夷州, 那是巴拉克·奥巴马出生的地方
will be closing its polls.
那里的投票站也即将关闭.
Idaho, Oregon  and Washington state,
爱达荷, 俄勒冈，还有华盛顿州
and those states  have been going Democratic
最近几年，这些州在总统竞选的过程中
in presidential contests  in recent years.
始终在坚持推行民主竞选
So in a few seconds
那么马上
those states  will be closing their polls,
这些州也即将关闭他们的投票站
and presumably we'll  be able to see what's...
我们大致可以推测出...
Louis!
路易斯!
...a major projection at that point.
...这是一个预测.
This is a moment that a lot of  people have been waiting for...
这是一个众人已期待许久的时刻...
Louis, come on down!  Come down!
路易斯, 下来，快下来!
...could be rather historic.
...也有可能是极具历史意义的一个时刻
And CNN can now project  that Barack Obama, 47 years old,
此刻，CNN基本可以推测出...
will become the President-Elect
现年47岁的巴拉克·奥巴马
of the United States. We project...
会成为美国的总统当选人
If there is anyone out there
我们预计...
who still doubts that America  is a place where
那些对于....  “在美国任何事情都有可能发生”
all things are possible...
这一说法持怀疑态度的人...
...who still wonders if the dream of our  founders is alive in our time,
那些想知道我们先辈的梦想是否还存在的人
who still questions  the power of our democracy,
那些对我们的民主的力量心怀疑虑的人
tonight is your answer.
今晚，你将会得到回答
You must look  through their eyes...
你一定要通过他们的眼睛...
...see what it is that they want...
...看出他们在想什么...
...see what it is that they need...
...看出他们需要什么...
...anticipate...
...预测...
...bring a smile  to the principal's eyes.
...要让你的服务对像露出笑容
Mr. Gaines.
盖恩斯先生.
I'm Admiral Rochon, the chief usher.
我是阿德米拉尔.罗尚, 首席接待员.
- Nice to meet you, admiral.  - Pleasure's all mine, sir.
- 很高兴见到你，阿德米拉尔.  - 无比荣幸，先生.
I just wanted to tell you  what an honor it is to meet you, sir.
我只是想告诉你能见到是多么地荣幸，先生
The honor is mine.
这也是我的荣幸
The president's so excited  to meet with you.
总统非常期待能见到你.
Well...
噢...
...that's just fine, isn't it?
...那很好，不是吗?
Let me show  you the way.
让我为你带路
I know the way.
我知道怎么走.
The heart of the question is,
核心问题是,
whether all Americans  are to be afforded equal rights
是否所有的美国人都享有同等的权利
and equal opportunities.
和同等的就业机会
It is the effort of American  Negroes to secure for themselves
这是美国黑人为了保护  他们自己的权益...
the full blessings of American life.
和实现所谓的美国梦  所付出的努力和取得的成就
We will respond  with that timeless creed
我们将用那历经时间考验的
振奋我们精神的不朽信条回应他们:
Yes, we can.
是的，我们可以.
谨以这部影片献给那些为了我们的自由  以及为了我们的公民权利而奋斗的人们
本片涉及的历史事件较多，如翻译过程中存在疏漏，请多多谅解.  翻译： @塔拉Tala
"I'll Close My Eyes"]